We discovered expanding universe. If we're expanding, it is vast in every metric we've ever established for it.
There are things that are vast in size, in temperature, in speed.
Just to get a feel for that, take a tree and expand it to be the size of the observable universe.
Then the Planck scale would expand roughly to the size of an atom.
So the Planck scale is to an atom as a tree is to the universe.
This very quickly leads you to have even greater existential dread because if you run the movie backwards, it gets to a point which seems quite catastrophic where these galaxies are literally on top of each other.
And eventually you're kind of imagining something that's so dense that you have to start thinking about as hot, soupy and chaotic.
The reason why you can't put quantum mechanics into it, it already seems to have quantum mechanics embedded in a deep and subtle way that Einstein himself didn't recognize.
Oh, please, to tell him, because my edible just kicked in and this is fascinating.
You can't put something into something into there.
We just don't know where it is inside of that thing, but once we find it in there, we're going to be like,
Oh, that's where it is! And we're like, I told you not to put it in there, it was already in there!
That simple, it's elegant, it's profound, it's amazing.
I agree.
So maybe it's not the photon being pulled, maybe the space itself is being warped and the photon is like surfing on the space.
So it's just like, yeah man, this wave is awesome!
And so you see it curve, right? But in that's the case.
Why can't it escape a black hole?
Because, you know, does that mean that the space inside of a black hole is being folded in, even the photons can't get pulled out?
Yeah, essentially.
What's happening?
Who's that happening?
Parkly.
But I want to be more than this.
He said, would you, can't be more than this, I said, why not?
He said it, because I'm more...
That's a stupid kind of thing.
There we go guys singing really, really low voice.
That's a proflindo.
It's like you can almost see the vocal chords right now.
Love, we're going over here.
Oh my god, that's pretty good.
Oh, that's a good vibe.
Love, we're going over here.
Nice job.
Love, love.
Love.
Hi, Juna.
Nice to meet you.
Number one.
Oh, the crowd is ready for it.
I got you.
No, I don't do the band.
I sit on it.
I just make a map like this.
So this is where in 1920, we didn't know if there were other galaxies.
A lot?
Yeah, I mean...
We thought we were the main character.
The Milky Way was the universe.
Yeah, yeah.
The manual comp, even in the 1700, imagined that some of these fuzzy things were island universes.
I can't hear his name without me.
So stop it.
Stop saying it.
Stop, you crazy.
But island universes?
I think so.
You think so?
I have fun, I'm in Leapass.
I was wondering if I could make it.
Can we have a V-Hack?
We're going to see the every...
Maybe I can come to Leapass.
Please.
Okay.
We're going to see the last three games.
The whole band is going to be a little bit more fast.
Okay.
What do you see?
Yeah, I just wanted to know.
I want to double check it now.
He's getting a little, he's getting a knuckle.
There.
So you're pretty fast.
Let me say...
He was like, he was like, yeah, he was like, this is a...?
Oh, that's a tough one.
Oh man, that's right.
Okay.
Oh man!
That was nice.
What do you got?
So before we begin, I just wanted...
I didn't know this until today that the two of you are actually current collaborators on some research.
Could you just highlight what that is?
What are you doing?
I mean, Brian and I have been working together for years.
Yeah.
Mostly, we've been thinking about extra spatial dimensions.
And different cosmological implications, implications for theoretical physics.
You know, hiding some dark energy and some extra dimensions.
As one does.
As one does, yes.
You're thinking about higher dimensions.
Yes.
Because the three plus time dimensions are not enough for you.
Well, you know, even Einstein, when he started working, wondered why three.
I mean, it's a curious question.
Once you start...
Well, it's a magic number.
Yeah.
It's a good or favorite number.
Thank you.
You're favorite number?
Wait, those are schoolhouse rock people right now.
They count to three.
They got it right away.
Okay, but how many dimensions are there, really?
We don't know, but certain theories tell us that it could be much more than the ones that meet the eye.
So it could be as many as ten or eleven.
Oh, like gender.
I said it, and now I'm getting arrested.
Did you just make up other dimensions?
I mean, it sounds like you're pulling it out of your ass.
I'm sorry.
Yeah, it's all over.
You didn't deny that immediately.
That was a great practice.
Okay.
Partly it is.
But it was also deep mathematical reasons that lead us to these ideas.
And we figure if nature can try some experiments, she will.
So every possibility might actually happen.
Okay.
So we're just exploring.
All right.
How about me?
Do you guys smoke?
All right.
So.
Please, I'll let you.
The microscope and telescope were invented 400 years ago.
And like I said, they take us to the grandest visions of our understanding of our place in the universe.
And the tiniest visions that also give us an understanding of our place in the universe.
And so this, those first steps were magnified at the dawn of the 20th century, especially through the 1920s.
And so let's start out with the large and we'll end with the small.
Okay.
So let's go back to the roaring 20s.
Let's just do that.
And here's something that it's hard to even believe that just 105 years ago, we didn't know if there were other galaxies.
We just thought all the stars in the night sky, the Milky Way was the entire universe.
We weren't given reason to think anything.
Oh, if there were these fuzzy things in the sky, okay, they're just fuzz.
We call them nebulae, which is Latin for fuzz.
Yes, thank you.
So we just thought it was just space-lint.
Yeah, yeah.
And but some fuzz, lint, face.
I'm not your message.
Nebulae, some nebulae were spiral shaped and others were irregular.
And the irregular ones were found in the plane of the galaxy, whereas the spiral ones were in every direction you looked.
Interesting.
So that was, oh, it was a first thing.
Well, maybe we can unpack this and figure out what's going on.
So there was a famous debate took place in 1920 at the national, hosted by the National Academy of Sciences, between Hebert D. Curtis.
Yes.
Unfortunately, that name.
And Harlow Shapley soon to become the director of the Harvard College Observatory.
And Hebert Curtis was director of the Allegheny Observatory.
Two very different...
Yeah, I'm going to say one of those sounds more expensive.
All right.
So they debated whether the spiral things were other galaxies, with a term coined by Immonual Kant in the 1700s,
who thought about this, philosopher.
Yes, Chuck?
No, Brian!
Brian did it to me, man.
What a Brian do to you.
Because he knows I can't hear the name Immonual Kant without being 12 years old.
Okay.
I'm so sorry.
So he's a philosopher, deep thinking philosopher, who looked up and he saw these spiral objects.
And he thought of them as possible island universes.
Oh, that's pretty cool.
And island universe.
That's beautiful.
Yeah.
That is.
But we didn't have evidence to say that, to support it, but it was a deep idea at the time.
So there they are, they debated this.
And...
But based on what evidence just hot taken?
They're scientists.
Okay.
All right.
Which means...
Sometimes we have rose colored glasses towards the past.
Yes, I get it.
So here's how it works.
Two scientists argue, there's a pact implicitly signed before they even begin.
Which is either you're right and she's wrong, you're right and he's wrong, or you're both wrong.
They know this going into the conversation.
It's nerd thunder dog.
So two scientists enter.
Two scientists leave.
But one's a little embarrassed.
Pay per view Saturday night.
Yeah.
So here's...
This is their Tyson Jake Paul, real kind of throw down.
So let's go to the Harvard fellow.
Yeah.
Because you can always tell a Harvard man, but you can't tell him much.
Oh, I got it.
So they were insufferable back then as well.
Got it.
Or they also like, I went to school in Boston.
I'd lost my fucking...
Fuck you.
Just say it.
So...
Say it.
You know?
I don't know.
All right.
So back to the...
Here's what happened.
Let's march.
Shappley was heavily invested in the entire night sky being part of the whole universe and the Milky Way.
And he had evidence at the time from a fellow astronomer who had looked at the spiral nebulae and claimed that he found them having moved on the sky.
Now, if you're really, really far away, that's essentially impossible to measure.
But if you're close up and you're moving, you can see that movement.
Okay?
Things that are close to you.
The example here is, if I see a plane moving across the sky and then I see a bird moving at the same angle, I don't conclude that the bird is going...
Yes, it's passing out.
...and the bird is much closer.
So at much lower speeds, I can see it across my field of view.
So because it's closer, that evidence suggested that the spiral nebulae were nearby.
And he... he bet on that horse.
But it was the wrong horse.
Oh, for sure.
He was doing what a good scientist will do. He took the data, put his confidence in the data.
It was later shown that the data he was basing his argument on was false.
It could not be verified by the work of other scientists.
In fact, no. The spiral nebulae had no motion across the sky.
And so, Shapley was just wrong.
Later, we would later show that he's wrong.
And what puts the nail in the coffin?
1923.
Edwin Hubble.
Oh, the man.
Hubble was a person before he was a telescope.
Yeah.
I thought he was born a telescope.
Born a telescope?
I just like when you're a kid, you're like, of course.
There was ninja turtles, and they were birthed.
Yeah, there it is.
So, he had an idea based on evidence, and it turned out to be wrong because the evidence was flawed.
So, there's some lessons there.
Right?
And if one scientist has one bit of evidence, you don't alert the authorities yet,
until there's confirming other experiments to do so.
That is what the peer review was all about.
That's peer review.
And by the way, for anybody who wants to know, scientists are haters.
Okay.
That is what they do.
You come up with something, and somebody goes, I call bullshit, and then it's on.
It's just on.
So, Neil, a peer review to us non-scientists is basically, it's scientific group chat,
and for you present your takeer information, and the 17 other friends that are in the group chat
get to be like, what's the bullshit?
And Sampley had a green bubble in the chat.
Oh, god damn.
God damn, what a horrible life to live.
He was the one green.
Surrounded by blues.
Yeah, and if you have an idea, and it's shown to be wrong, then it's just wrong.
In fact, Einstein, after his relativity, which we'll get into in a couple of minutes,
that was hard to accept by people, right?
It was hard.
It was very counterintuitive.
Someone came up with a work saying 100 against Einstein.
100 against Einstein.
And then he's rumored to say what after that?
Let's say I just learned this anecdote, but he's rumored to have said,
why 100 if I'm wrong, one would have been enough.
Wow.
Yeah.
It's pretty great.
And believe me, I've been married for 27 years.
That is right.
Okay, so here's what happened.
So Edwin Hubble is curious about the spiral nebulae.
And he finds a star in them that matches a kind of star that's not in a nebulae.
It's just sort of nearer by than that star.
And it's a very specific kind of variable star, named after the very first of its kind,
Cepheid variable.
The first of its kind was found in the constellation Cepheus.
And so that's how we categorize types of variable stars.
The first one in a constellation, all the others, no matter where you find them, are that variety.
Found a Cepheid variable there.
And what was spent, tell us what's special about the Cepheid variables.
Well, they have a very predictable property where their luminosity, how bright they shine,
is related to a sort of oscillation.
And so you can tell that you're looking at precisely one of those.
It's very easily identifiable.
If you get the luminosity out of it, then you can say I can see the period vary.
Right.
Based on that period, I know how bright it should be.
How bright it should be.
So it says, though, you knew your light bulb, right?
You can tell if you have a very bright light bulb far away or a very dim light bulb up close.
Of course. Right.
How can you distinguish the two?
And how do you distinguish the two if you know nothing about the light bulb?
But if you know everything about your light bulb, you know exactly what it is, then you can say,
oh, I know this light bulb, so I know exactly how far away.
So he says this star is of this particular luminosity.
And the only way it can be that dim is if it is far out of it.
You know, everything happens in space.
And space is happening in space time.
In the four dimensions of space time, there can never be a time without a place and vice versa.
If I say meet me, you will need to know where and what time to make that happen.
Regardless of the place throughout the entire universe.
Well, how would you like to give the gift of space time?
Suppose I told you you could mark any occasion with a beautiful physical representation of its corresponding space time.
Well, thanks to our friends at Under Lucky Stars.
You can do just that.
Under Lucky Stars makes beautifully designed star maps that show the unique alignment of the stars in a place and date chosen by you.
Whether it's a birthday and engagement wedding or when you first met, the stars never look the same twice.
Each star map can be personalized with your unique title and footnote.
Now, I have three children.
I gave each one of them a birthday star map.
Each one has the same message.
This is the sky under which Morgan entered the universe.
This is the sky under which Aiden entered the universe.
And this is the sky under which Charlie entered the universe.
And they love it.
And so will your mother, brother, sister, father, wife, child, best friend, or even your boss, you know, if you're that kind of employee.
Because you're giving them the most unique commemoration of a significant life event that they will always cherish.
So don't wait.
You can even go super meta and give them a star map of the day.
You gave them a star map.
All right, okay, maybe I'm prone to being a little extreme, but perhaps you'll just start with an important date.
Go to underluckystars.com and immortalize the happiest moments of your life.
That's underluckystars.com.
And now, back to the space time that is the show.
It's important to know what he actually meant by that because Hubble himself never was convinced that these were actually other galaxies.
He proved that there was something beyond the outskirts of our galaxy.
We know our galaxy about 100,000 light years across.
His analysis showed this to be 900,000 light years.
We now updated it to 2 million light years.
But Hubble was so conservative that he was unwilling to then say this is an island universe.
Is this a galaxy in a stone right?
What is it, idiot?
What's the difference just from a space real estate standpoint?
What's the difference between an island universe and a galaxy?
What are we talking about?
They're poetically identical.
The same.
They're the same.
Pohedically identical.
Got it.
Yeah.
Because if our galaxy is our universe and is another galaxy, then you get to call that a universe.
Except once we see the full breadth of it all, we got to reallocate how we use the word universe.
Because it's universe.
One.
One verse.
Right.
But we're in the multi-versus.
Spider-Man.
We're in the.
We'll get to that.
Okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
We'll get to that.
All right.
Minus the spider-man.
But we'll.
You didn't like the second one.
I thought it was great.
So, so, Janet, how did we reeling from the fact that we are not the universe.
We're just a part of a universe.
And then a few years later, Hubble discovers that the spiral nebulae are in motion, body and soul.
So, what's going on there?
Yeah.
So, once he's starting to be able to use these cephyde variables in these standard candles to get a strong sense of how far away things are, he can start to do that.
He can start to do that kind of mapping out the local environment, what we have right nearby.
And then also galaxies further away.
These little smudges on the sky.
And he begins to catalog not only that there are other galaxies around us, that create distances, but there also seem to be receding away from us.
Largely, predominantly.
Yeah.
So, he makes a plot.
Makes a plot.
So, this is very strange.
I mean, you're looking at all of these enormous galaxies.
So, a galaxy's a collection of hundreds of billions of stars.
And they're pretty localized.
And maybe they're spirals and blobs.
And they're very far away.
And they're also moving away from us in every direction.
That's a peculiar.
So, he makes this plot.
It's completely freaky.
But it gets freaky because the further away they are, the faster they're expanding away from us.
And they're calculating this all without computers.
Well.
Hundreds of billions of stars.
People were called computers back then.
Sure.
So, yeah, they should.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
They should.
Yeah.
Look at the work computer.
A person who I have to use.
Yeah.
So.
Well, wait.
And there's a room full of.
And yes, but they're doing it without the machines.
The lecture list.
So, he actually uses the work of one of the Harvard computers, which was a woman named Henrietta Levitt.
And she was part of a group of women who worked at the Harvard Observatory that were called...
And she would talk like this.
Of course.
Well, they were called Pickering's Herm because Charles Pickering, at one point, was so frustrated with his male computers.
That he fired them all and he said, my maid could do a better job and he hired his maid.
Who was Willemina Fleming and she did a great job.
And she hired all these other women and one of them was Henrietta Levitt.
And she made 30 cents an hour.
Can I hand that in?
Can I give you a hand?
Are we applauding her or her pay?
That was weird.
30 cents an hour.
She should be making iPhone.
Okay.
So.
I said it.
I said.
That's up.
So, but mixed in here, we've got simultaneous things going on.
Einstein's general theory of relativity is already at the races.
Okay.
So that came in in 1915.
15.
Okay.
That gave us a mechanism to understand what the whole universe could be doing that just catches up on that.
Well, Einstein writes down his equations in 1915.
And initially he applies them to things like the motion of the Earth around the Sun and terrestrial and nearby motion.
Okay.
Local things.
But then some other very creative thinkers, one in particular was a Belgian priest named George Lomatra.
He decides to apply the mathematics not to something in the universe, but to the entirety of the universe.
And find from the equations that the universe should be expanding over time.
It should be slowly.
But it should be clear.
He was able to do that not based on his training as a priest.
He was a priest physicist.
He was a priest physicist, but no doubt his interest in applying these ideas to the entirety of the universe was not distinct from his focus on the big questions of existence.
That they weren't that separate, although he in his own mind was very clear.
He said there are two ways to have deep insight about the world.
There's mathematics and there's salvation.
And he said, let me follow both.
And that's what he did.
But not intermingled.
He was very clear not to it.
There was a line in the sand.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
So, so, so, lemmatra.
I'll let you guys figure out the pronunciation.
So, he takes the equations.
We have an expanding universe, but he, so lemacher.
Before, before, the mantra predicts an expanding universe using Einstein's equations.
So Einstein could have made the prediction and he didn't.
Yeah, in fact, in 1917 Einstein actually got there first.
And when he applied the equations to the entire space, was very disturbed.
That he couldn't get a universe that met his own philosophical prejudice.
Which was?
That the universe is fixed, eternal, static, and unchanged.
Why would anybody think the universe could be anything other than that?
Well, I mean, there is this book called Genesis, which seems to suggest a beginning.
Okay.
So there are some people who think perhaps that that vision is not correct.
But Einstein and many others at the time very firmly believed that the universe could not change on the largest of scales.
And that's just a philosophical bias.
Totally.
And in fact, he changes.
Wait, wait, wait, how could he get away with that?
If all the galaxies have gravity, and if they all feel each other's gravity, they would all collapse down into one point.
Yeah, so this was an argument that Isaac Newton actually gave,
actually gave, hundreds of years earlier, but if the universe is infinitely big,
and if the galaxies are spread across the infinity of space, then there is no center for them to collapse toward.
Yeah.
So you can envision a static universe now.
If it's infinite.
And only if it's infinite.
But even more than that, Einstein then, in his own general relativity, recognized basically the issue that you're raising in a finite universe.
And he said, let me introduce a repulsive push to counter the attractive pull of gravity.
And that's an anti-gravity force field called the cosmological constant.
So he introduces this into the map in 1917.
It was not in the 1915 equations.
He introduces it just to have a static universe that will allow him to breathe easy.
And to fulfill his philosophical bias.
Then the mantra says, we can have an expanding universe.
And so how did Einstein react to that?
Einstein learns of this from the matra in 1927.
And he says to the matra, your calculations are correct, but your physics is abominable.
Oh, it ends fighting words.
It's right.
By which it was saying, you can't trust that every mathematical calculation tells you something real about reality.
And some math should be in math textbooks, and it's interesting, but it's nothing more than a mathematical curiosity.
And he says, let me try your idea of an expanding universe.
That's a mathematical curiosity. It's not real.
Okay, so then 1929, Hubble discovers an expanding universe.
Now what? What happens next?
Well, so it's interesting because the way I originally described it as kind of confusing, you might think it makes it seem like we're at the center of this expansion and everything's receding away from us.
But the way the Hubble law is specifically, it's much more like the space between every galaxy is actually stretching.
So from their point of view, if you were on one of those other galaxies, it would also look like anything you're receiving away from.
Right. Everything's receding away from it.
And if you imagine that it's not the galaxies literally moving on space time, but actually the distance between the galaxies that's stretching, then something further ways actually moving away from you faster.
There was more space stretching, and this was really closer to the matrix description, not even closer.
It simply wasn't static.
So just so I'm clear, at that time they believed there's only one galaxy, and approximately 1925, just so I'm following.
I feel like I'm in a chrysanolin right now watching tenet. Let me just pause real quick.
No, not at all at the time.
2324, one galaxy.
One galaxy, it was one, it was one, it was one universe, one universe copy.
Yes.
How many universes are we in now?
But are you talking island universes or are you talking universe universe?
I'm talking about the whole thing.
Oh good god, there's one universe that we know about.
Built with 100 billion galaxies, each of which has on the order of 100 billion stars, there are theoretical ideas that Niel suggests we might get to tomorrow.
That speak to the possibility there might be other universes.
So the answer is we don't know for sure, but the data seems to suggest that there's one universe.
Well we were talking about this backstage, if the delta is that big between those two numbers, which is one, and this is just basically the set of Gagilian.
How do we know that what we're living in right now, the data that we know right now isn't going to be wildly off in 50 years from now or 100 years from now, they'll be like look at those dumbdums in 2020.
We hope that that's what will happen.
We live to be wrong.
We're scientists.
Oh god.
We live to be wrong.
Got it.
Okay.
So let's follow through this reasoning.
We discovered expanding universe.
If we're expanding, that means we're bigger today than we were yesterday.
And bigger yesterday than we were the day before.
So logically, where does that take us?
Bigger.
Oh, I'm sorry.
So yes.
If you're already disturbed about the lack of permanence to the universe, then this very quickly leads you to have even greater existential dread because if you run the movie backwards,
then everything was once closer together.
And if you keep running the movie backwards, it gets to a point which seems quite catastrophic where these galaxies are literally on top of each other.
And eventually, you're kind of imagining something that's so dense that you have to start thinking about as hot and soupy and chaotic and then what?
What a lemon for Polish.
Yes.
So the major basically said, look, if the math is saying that the universe is expanding today, and if then Hubble's data shows that the universe is expanding today, just whine the cosmic film in reverse, you run the film backwards and things get closer and closer together.
And there are suggestions that there's a point in the distant past when everything was on top of everything else, and he calls us the primeval atom.
This is the beginning, according to his description.
How can I happen to know if there was an astronomer active at the time, brilliant guy named Fred Hoyl, who was not into a universe that would be changing.
He knew the universe was expanding, he couldn't reason that away.
Accepted that.
Yeah, accepted that.
But if you're expanding, but you're always the same, that must mean matter is being spontaneously created in the void to create new galaxies so that statistically, the universe always looks the same.
But here's the thing, if the universe is expanding that in itself is a change, so why would you not accept a changing universe?
Because he wanted to always look the same for all of time, for all eternity in the past and in the future.
Again, it's a philosophical bias.
But I think the idea of the beginning was particularly disturbing.
The idea, so this primedial atom that lamatures.
It's disturbing the scientists, but not for religious people where God made the universe.
They're perfectly happy with the beginning.
Pope Pius XII, perhaps the nerdiest pope in history who loves science.
Why do you know this?
He didn't, I don't know.
He took the lamatures work and he said, there is the scientific evidence for Genesis.
That's what he said.
And when Lamature heard this, he threw a fit.
Belgian priest, Lamature.
That's right.
Not directly, but yes, when he catches wind that this is what the pope is saying.
And one of his students who was in the class, the lamature had to teach that afternoon after learning.
He said that the major who normally was very quiet, mild-mannered.
He came in and ranted for 45 minutes because his whole point was, I am not blending my religious life and my scientific life.
And here the pope is taking my scientific work and he's turning into religion.
But notice, he said all that to a student and not the pope.
You don't want to know the Galileo situation.
So I have a tamer version of that quote.
As far as I see, such a theory of the primeval atom remains entirely outside any metaphysical or religious question.
Yeah, that's after I had a couple drinks and children.
Okay, so then I got called the Big Bang by Fred Hoyle.
Yeah, so Fred Hoyle was in a 1948 BBC radio interview.
Why do you even know this level?
I don't care about that.
Okay.
And so he is describing his own approach, which as you mentioned is a steady state approach where matter is created spontaneously and fills in the gaps in space.
And so they ask him about this other approach, not his.
And he says, oh, that theory in which all matter must be created in one Big Bang.
And that's where the idea of Big Bang theory comes from.
Now, people have interpreted that as a derogatory description.
His own way of recounting the story is he was simply trying to draw a distinction between a theory in which in his steady state, only a little bit of matter is created here in the air cross space versus this other theory.
Like one hydrogen atom per century per cubic light year.
There's some small rate.
Not quite that small.
So it is one atom per century per Olympic-sized swimming pool.
Oh, okay. That's all that you need.
And so it's kind of an amazing.
In the whole universe.
Yeah, yeah.
Because what's more believable that one little atom forms in a swimming pool size arena of space per century or that there's this moment where everything is created all at once.
Framing it that way, his theory sounds perhaps a little bit more believable.
Or less, less crazy.
Yeah.
Yeah. So what do we have to assume if there is a Big Bang?
So we've got to assume that the expansion has been uniform the whole time.
Not necessarily.
It doesn't have to be uniform.
No.
Yeah, it can change over time.
Oh, that's been always expanding.
It's always expanding.
Okay.
And-
And lesser's extra dimensions.
That's my-
Alright.
So can expand differently in a-
Brian and I are talking about this way.
Well, yeah, you can squeeze the other dimensions.
There could have been chaotic mixing of the expansion and contraction, but overall, the overall volume of the universe was expanding.
But the way you get this is looking at the rate at which the universe is expanding.
Yes.
And that is a slope on a graph.
And Hubble first derived that.
And it's-
There's a slope.
And it's just-
He called it a letter C, which is for constant.
But since then, we swapped that out with a capital H for Hubble.
And we called it the Hubble constant.
Yeah.
Very famous Hubble constant.
So it's constant over space.
Yeah, it's important to realize-
It's not very-
It's really the Hubble parameter we should call it, because it does change in time.
It was-
It could have been faster in the early universe, faster in the future.
Alright, so Hubble, he had the wrong-turned-out-
The Sephede variable he used, he didn't know at the time, there were two varieties of Sephede variables.
The one that's near us and the one that you can see from far away.
And he presumed they were the same, no reason to think otherwise.
Right.
So he got the wrong distance, the wrong expansion rate of the universe.
So Sephede is like diabetes, is type 1 and type-
Yes, there's a type 1 and type 2.
Exactly, I think.
Maybe not exactly.
Yes, there's literally type 1, Sephede and type 2, Sephede.
And you got to use apples and apples when you're doing this exercise.
So he got an age in the universe of two billion years.
We would later refine these numbers.
Why and I was in graduate school many moons ago.
The uncertainty in the Hubble concert was a factor of two.
There was a ten-
So with the-
With the Hubble concert, you run the film backwards.
Ask how much time at this expansion rate looking backwards, when do we get to time zero?
That makes sense.
Yeah, just when is everybody in the same place at the same time?
That's a perfectly sensible question.
And we got two number, there are two camps, a ten billion year camp and a 20 billion year camp.
A whole factor of two.
And everyone is fighting for their-
And we know they both can't be right.
And so we need better data.
One of the goals of-
Wait, isn't being off by ten billion quite a bit?
That's a lot.
Again, the median and I only took physics one.
Okay.
In undergrad, I did not advance, I don't want the smoke, but I am saying being off by ten billion.
There's a lot.
Here's a thing.
Like if you go out to dinner and we split it and I'm off.
That big of a delta.
If I'm, yeah, if I'm a hundred percent off.
Yes.
Aren't you like you lose your science little thing?
No, so.
You know what I mean?
Like if it's a disbard.
Yeah.
Here's a thing.
But you know, you just get to talk your shit.
You are off by ten billion.
You get to talk your shit still.
Here's a thing.
Like my dad in the living room when he's giving his opinions about politics.
He just gets to run his mouth continuously.
I got this.
Go ahead.
This is me and my dad thing.
But I'm just a little mad that a capital S scientist was this off.
Okay.
Go ahead.
And that was a second question.
The universe is vast.
Yes.
In time.
Yeah.
And in space.
Sure.
It is vast.
In every metric we've ever established for it.
There are things that are vast in size.
In temperature.
In speed.
In gravity.
And so if I'm off by a factor of two.
Between ten billion and twenty billion.
Yeah.
I could have been off by a factor of ten.
By a factor of a thousand.
By a factor of a million.
We were quite happy.
We were in the same sandbox.
Having that conversation.
So it's kind of like being Jeff Bezos.
If I'm off by ten billion.
Not so bad.
So.
Could I also ask you the second philosophical question which is?
Sure.
Which is.
No, no, no.
This is real.
When you were like, it's either ten billion or twenty billion.
And I was asking you this backstage which was,
when the number is that big, is it almost like the United States is a debt?
Where they're like, the deficit is at twenty eight trillion.
And you're like, what does it even matter now?
Yeah, but it's at a good, Jillian, Manillion.
Like, what does it matter?
Well, why does the number, because I feel like a freshman in college.
It's going to matter in awful lot.
Stop.
I would say that actually ten billion is actually quite good ten to twenty.
It's very much in the ballpark because.
You should run the federal reserve.
Yeah.
You know what I mean?
It's a good way to think about it.
You could have been off by a trillion.
Well, but the future is going to be much, much longer than the past.
So it's not as though the universe kind of will expire within another ten billion years.
Like we're confined to this number.
The future could be just a huge number.
We could be living in a time where it's not ten billion.
It's a kind of way where we're going to be perhaps, these are all very, very good answers.
Perhaps one other way of looking at it.
It was a bad question.
We don't care whether it's ten billion or twenty billion.
The number doesn't matter.
What does matter is...
That's the most American answer, by the way.
That's the most American answer.
The truth is we don't care, but we want our theories to work.
We want our theories to make predictions that match with observations.
That's the only thing that matters to us.
The actual answer that comes out whether it's ten billion or fifty billion...
Or forty trillion.
Like you're saying it just doesn't matter.
What we need to have a consistent description so that we have evidence that we know what we're doing.
Because evidence is bad.
Both sides could not be right.
And so when the Hubble telescope was launched, okay, I'm just getting out of graduate school.
It is launched.
The number one goal set for that telescope was to resolve that discrepancy.
The telescope's named after the guy who gave us the Hubble specimen in the first place.
Within two or three years, we nailed it.
And the Hubble constant, its value would give us an age of the universe at about fourteen billion years.
Which is comfortably between those two extremes.
And that's science working at its best.
There's a limit to how much we can keep beating each other over the head.
Let's get more data.
Let's build a telescope that'll solve this.
And in fact, today there is a similar argument happening.
It's not between 20 billion and 10 billion, which as you say is a factor of two or a hundred percent difference.
Now we're down to the five percent difference.
We understand things that well, that we have two groups that are five percent apart, describing a number of years, billions of years into the past.
And that's the precision with which we can do it within five percent.
And they're killing each other.
So again, we don't care the exact number.
We care that we can describe it with that level of precision when we're talking about events that happen billions of years ago.
That's the mind bending.
And here's the issue.
When it was 10 and 20 billion, you always have to report your uncertainties for a number in science.
And those uncertainties had a little bit of overlap in the middle and it landed where you expected it to land.
And now that we have two other warring factions on the value of the Hubble constant, those two numbers are within five percent of each other, but the uncertainties are tight.
So the uncertainties don't overlap.
And if you look at go Google search on Hubble tension, and that's what will come up.
Adam Reese is coming to pay new works in October.
I just planted an ad.
Adam Reese, you know about prize.
One of the Nobel Prize winners who discovered that the universe is not just expanding the expansions getting ever faster.
It's accelerating who is part of this Hubble tension debate.
We'll be speaking at pioneer on the Hubble network.
Without waxing philosophical, I just don't want to miss this point that we're not actually saying, which is what makes science so incredibly great is exactly what you all just demonstrated.
It is this pursuit of the truth based upon the best available information at the time.
So it's okay if it's wrong because when it's right, we're going to get there.
Yes.
You got it.
All right. So we're turning the clock back and we get to the big bang.
And but now the universe, large skill universe described by general relativity is now small.
It is so small you extend the equations go back.
The universe is the size of an atom.
Does quantum physics apply to the entire universe or only to atoms?
Where are you on that? Both of you.
Well, at this point we feel we have to invoke quantum mechanics to understand what was happening in the big bang.
The energy scales are so dramatic and that we're really probing quantum physics.
High energies, you're really looking so much surprisingly at small scales.
So we are still trying to grapple with what the big bang is telling us about the potential to understand not just general relativity but a kind of quantum variant of that.
If there is such a thing.
Yeah. So I got general relativity and I got quantum physics.
Do they make nice in the sandbox?
That's a deep and difficult question and one that I and many others have spent their lives trying to answer.
And we do not fully let me answer yet.
Let me restate that.
Yeah.
That you and others have spent your lives failing to answer.
Yes. Okay.
Agreed.
But I said that by a slightly said that.
Okay.
I hear that.
Ah, take that.
Okay, you got a fan over here.
Right. So no, it's exactly the case.
So when you take Einstein's equations of the general theory of relativity and you try to invoke quantum mechanics within the same calculations,
which as you eloquently noted, you'd have to do.
If you're talking about the whole universe when it's incredibly small, you need Einstein's general theory of relativity to the whole universe after all.
But you also need quantum physics because it is so small and that's the theory that describes the small things.
And when you try to simply put the equations together, you get one answer out from almost any calculation, which is infinity.
And that might sound old. That's interesting.
A big, deep mystical number. No, it's nonsense.
Infinity is nature's way of grabbing us by the lapel and slapping us around and saying you're doing something wrong.
You've got to figure this out.
So I put another one. That's what.
Infinity is where God divides by zero.
Yes.
Stephen Hawking.
Oh, Stephen Hawking said that.
Well, at least that's for these attributed.
Okay.
So, but you say they don't make nice in the sandbox.
Yeah.
So there's a limit.
What's this plank length?
What's going on there?
Well, the plank length is the scale at which.
It's named after who?
After Mox Plunk.
I love how you say Mox.
I don't know.
What do you think of my time?
I say Max Plunk.
I know.
Max, okay.
Well, a hundred years ago in the early discoveries of quantum mechanics was thinking about whether the universe was discrete or if it really was a continuum.
And if I looked, for instance, at the air in this room, if I look closer and closer, do I find that it's actually made of individual molecules moving around and is not actually continuum and same with water and was thinking about these things.
So in other words, water is not infinitely divisible.
You get to molecule at some point.
Eventually you get to an individual quanta, a little particulate, a discrete bundle.
And in thinking about this, there was sort of a fundamental scale that we would say is when we can definitely no longer think in a way where we're ignoring this quantum scale.
Where we're forced as Brian is describing beyond that, we're definitely going to strike an infinity.
But by the Plunk, Lunk, we're in trouble.
We really should be trying to understand the theory of gravity at a quantum level.
Maybe that means that space time is coming in little individual bundles.
I don't even know how to think about that.
I'm just thinking about correlations between little tiny space time is coming.
Yeah.
That was a wild sense.
That was very game of thrones.
Space time is coming.
Well, I mean, if it came from the big bang, I mean, was it the moment that space and time was in fact created?
And are we thinking about things of a continuum of space time itself?
Brian, how big is that smallest unit?
The Plank and I have to 10 to the minus 33 centimeters.
And again, I know the question will be, well, how do you think about something that so that's all what is it?
What is it?
10 to the minus 33 or 10 to the minus 31?
And again, don't care about the exact value, but that's where the mathematics takes us.
And just to get a feel for that, if you were to take an atom and take a tree.
Take a tree and expand it to be the size of the observable universe.
A tree.
Then the Plank scale that 10 to the minus 33 centimeters would expand roughly to the size of an atom.
So the Plank scale is to an atom as a tree is to the universe.
That's how tiny the distance we're talking about here.
And why?
I'm going to channel.
And so you mentioned this with a ruler?
I know.
I'm going to channel.
Can I channel you right now?
You can channel me.
I'm not going to even pretend like I understand what's happening right now.
Maybe 100% honest.
There's like 3,500 people here and I'm like, don't act like you know.
No.
I'm going to channel.
You lost me at space time is coming.
And by the way, you came in quite hot, Brian.
And you're like, I know what you're thinking.
And that's not what I was thinking.
I was thinking.
I think it's really incredible.
Let's just have a quick little tangent here.
It is almost 9 p.m.
And this many people went on ticketmaster.com.
And you're like, paid fees.
You way back there.
Up there.
Yes.
Way up there.
Yeah.
You guys paid tickets to learn about space and epilite.
It was very heartening.
So that's what I was thinking about, Brian.
Actually, like, you know when people say this country is going to shit.
And math and science is at an all time low.
I'm like, you know what?
It's the math and science lovers.
I feel the real thing in theater.
On a...
You know.
Of all things you can be doing at 9 p.m.
Just...
So, so I'm channeling...
How's that on here?
Sure.
What?
Why do you have any confidence at all that you know what's happening on a scale that's small?
We don't.
Oh, okay, that's it.
That's it.
Come on, come on.
Thank you guys.
We don't know anything.
We have to be off by a whole lot.
Good night.
Take care.
Thank you, begin.
No, no.
So, so let me see if I can unpack this.
Yeah.
Is it true we're going to figure it out right now?
Okay.
Sure.
Is it true that every prediction we've ever made with quantum physics when we've been able to test it has come true?
Absolutely.
Okay.
Well, that's true.
That's right.
General relativity, we already know what its boundaries are because there are calculations you cannot make because of this infinity problem.
Absolutely.
Therefore, if one of those is going to succumb to the other, it sounds like Einstein has to...
He's going to have to bow down to the quantum.
That's what's happening.
Bend the knee to the quantum.
So either quantum will absorb Einstein or there's a higher level understanding that'll absorb them both.
Yeah.
That's true.
But also quantum isn't in competition.
We have theories of matter, for instance nuclear forces that we understand, they can be quantized.
Theory of electromagnetism can be quantized.
So there are laws of physics and quantum mechanics is a regime in which we're understanding the highest energy attributes of those laws of physics.
Now, gravity, Einstein's general relativity, is replaced the theory of gravity with this theory of space time, this theory of geometry.
The place Newton's theory of gravity.
But it is one of those forces that should sit with the matter forces and have a classical regime, meaning a regime which we don't worry about quantum mechanics, things look smooth.
We understand general relativity works beautifully.
Regime sounds very political.
Very good.
It does.
Tate.
Totally does.
Very U.S.S.R.
It sounds very...
Unfortunately, she was in light.
Everywhere.
But then when we go to the early universe, like the Big Bang or in the course of black holes, where things start to get very extreme, we want to be able to quantize that law of physics.
As we have quantized other things.
It's not going to replace gravity.
Exactly.
We want to quantize gravity.
And that seemed like a perfectly reasonable request.
So Einstein's equations are not quantized.
They require continuum.
So how do you quantize gravity?
Good.
So, Jan is describing the history as very insightful and useful.
So, we had an equation for electricity and magnetism that came from Maxwell.
We were able to blend that with quantum mechanics, giving us quantum electrodynamics.
It works.
We had equations describing the strong and weak nuclear forces.
We were able to embed quantum mechanics into those theories, works wonderfully well.
When we try to play exactly the same game with Einstein's theory of gravity, general relativity, and try to put quantum mechanics in there to quantize it, it just doesn't work.
So, what does that mean?
Well, it means you're not smart enough to...
Well, it's an interesting.
It could be that we're not smart enough.
And I'm full well willing to take that as the ultimate answer.
But there's a lot of evidence if you allow me to come right up till today for just a moment.
I know you want to go to the end.
This is the Centennial.
But go ahead.
There is evidence today that Einstein's general relativity, the reason why you can't quantize it, the reason why you can't put quantum mechanics into it, it already seems to have quantum mechanics embedded in a deep and subtle way that Einstein himself didn't recognize.
Oh, please, to tell him, because my edible just kicked in, and this is fascinating.
I mean, what you're saying right now is revolutionary, because what you're saying is you can't put something into something in there.
If it's already there, we just don't know where it is inside of that thing.
But once we find it in there, we're going to be like, yo, that's where it is.
And we're like, I told you not to put it in there, it was already in there.
Okay, check the...
Amazing!
Check the blue and gasket, we got it.
No, that is like, that's simple, it's elegant, it's profound, it's amazing.
I agree.
Alright, so let's back up, back to the Roaring Twenties.
And I just want to go down the list of completely freaky things that quantum physics prescribed that defied anybody's common sense, and which is why it's still freaky.
In fact, what's that quote from, was it Feynman about quantum physics, what did he say?
Yeah, there are a few, but if you think about quantum mechanics without getting dizzy, you haven't understood a single thing about it.
Oh, and I understand it very well.
Okay, so, 1923, the Wave Particle Duality is proposed.
So, that's kind of freaky.
Yeah.
That particles are also waves.
Yeah, it was Prince Louis DeBroy.
Who, basically...
He was a prince?
Yeah, and so he said, look, in 1905 Einstein showed us that light, which we had thought of as a wave, actually needs to be described as a particle.
So called photoelectric effect, now we wait till...
1905.
And then in 1923, in his PhD thesis, Louis DeBroy says, let me do the reverse.
Electrons, we always think about them as particles, maybe they need to be thought of as waves.
And that is a key moment in...
Wasn't his PhD thesis like, that was a prince who did that?
A prince.
A prince?
I don't believe it.
I know current monarchy, not that intelligent.
That's me honest.
Harry or William, you're not cooking.
You're not cooking this up.
There's too much incest.
You know this, you understand science, for you to be operating at that level.
So not buying it.
Nope.
You cheated off someone's paper, not buying it.
So his PhD thesis, if I remember correctly, was like 12 pages long or something.
Very short.
And he got a Nobel Prize for that.
He got a Nobel Prize.
He got a Nobel Prize for a 12 page.
PhD.
The PhD paper.
Yeah.
Okay, let me just say, that's the smartest dude ever.
Well, that's how you know he was royalty.
He turned into a 12 page.
12 page.
He made me cook it.
Like, Dr. Prince.
And he thought, thank you.
Double space, 12 page.
PhD paper.
No, no.
The tighter margin.
You entitled me to shit.
A couple of years later.
No, so, Neil, you just, I'm sorry, Neil.
I shouldn't have spoken ill of the monarchs there.
No, no, this, I got nothing.
This is a market.
We just want to war to get away from the monarch.
That's for long.
Stop, stop.
Stop.
Just give it time.
Fine.
Okay.
So.
So then, Schrodinger came around.
Oh, we have a Schrodinger fan of him.
That was the cat.
Yeah.
The cat.
So, what did Schrodinger do for us?
Well, Schrodinger begins to think more abstractly about what's real and what's not real.
So, we're used to thinking of particles.
You've already described De Broglie and the electron.
We think of these little fundamental particles, almost like billiard balls, acting out their lives.
And they have some concrete existence.
Schrodinger starts to say, well, there's wave particle duality that's pretty profound.
But maybe the only thing that's real is this thing called the wave function, which is the probability for the particle to be in a certain state, to be in a certain location, to be moving with a certain speed.
But the particle itself, in some sense, isn't real anymore.
If you look for it, sometimes you'll find it in a concrete location.
But what is really determined by equations, by the laws of physics, is the wave function, which is this probabilistic description.
And the wave function occupies physical space, doesn't it?
Yeah, the wave function occupies physical space and tell you.
Only for a single particle.
So, it's a kind of important subtletay.
Yeah.
For one particle, you can think about this wave function as filling space.
If there are two particles, it lives in six dimensional space.
If there are three particles, it's in nine dimensional space.
So, you really can't think of it in these ordinary terms.
Oh, I am, huh?
Well, okay.
So, if the particle can be anywhere here, and I have some barrier here, it could show up on the other side of the barrier.
Right, but it doesn't actually travel through.
So, let's say your barrier is a concrete wall.
If there's some small probability that you would find the particle, the wave function would describe the probability of finding the particle in this region.
But it doesn't actually like a billiard ball travel through this map wall.
Okay, but this might be the THC talking.
But the way you guys are talking, there just might just be one particle.
Like, there aren't bunch of particles.
It's just one particle.
I told you he blew a gasket.
Well, but Richard Feynman had the idea that maybe there was one particle that circled around through time.
And cycled back over and over again, giving what appeared to be many particles now, but there's only a single particle through this temporal cycle.
So, you're right.
That's the target.
Moving forward and backwards through time.
Oh, my God.
Okay.
All right.
So, but what I'm saying is if a particle can show up on the other side of the barrier, then that you guys came up with a word for that.
And it's tunneling quantum time.
It's a quantum tunnel through the barrier, but that's the point of the short answer saying, what's real is just this probabilistic likelihood of finding the particle.
The particle itself in some sense does not have concrete existence anymore.
Okay.
So, it challenges the whole nature of reality.
No, but, but concretely, there is a probability that we could calculate for the likelihood of you tunneling through the stage and being underneath the floor.
And it's a non-zero probability.
It's kind of small.
So, it's unlikely to happen, but that's what quantum mechanics tells us.
But the smaller I get, the more likely it will happen.
Exactly.
It can happen in the laboratory.
Yeah. Okay.
So, just for context here.
Wow.
We were trying to understand how the sun made energy.
And we did the calculation.
Once we determined the sun is mostly hydrogen and it's hottest in the center, we said it must be undergoing fusion.
And so, what you run the mass to undergo fusion of proton, the nucleus of a hydrogen atom, has to merge with another proton, the nucleus of another hydrogen atom.
Protons have the same charge.
Electrostatically, light charges repel.
So, they have to be moving fast enough so that before they have a chance to repel, they stick together and form a new nucleus.
Okay.
We calculated what temperature that was necessary, because high temperatures give you higher speed.
We calculated that temperature and was 100 million degrees, and there was no way the center of the sun was going to give us 100 million degrees.
Because you can calculate through sensible laws of thermodynamics what that should be, and we were scratching our heads.
And the quantum physics comes around, and then you invent this spooky magical thing called tunneling.
And we discover in our calculations that at a mere 10 million degrees, see these, this matters, 10 million, 100 million degrees.
At a mere 10 million degrees, they would otherwise not hit, but some of them tunnel through and connect.
Tunneling makes the sun's energy production even possible.
And I was like,
because it's not just something that particle physicists worry about in their laboratory, I have to worry about it as an astrophysicist.
Why are you worried about this? It's okay.
Thank you.
The sun's going to sun.
Hellrovens, let them, let the sun do that.
It's okay.
Okay, Neil, don't blow up that.
Okay, so tunneling.
A lot of things.
There's a lot tunneling, and.
So what about the Heisenberg uncertainty principle?
That seems like the biggest thing of them all. Talked me through that real fast.
Yeah, I was saying so. That's the real moment when the old ways of looking at the world are shown they have to be jettisoned.
Because the old way of looking at the world, what is reality?
Rality is stuff that's at a location moving with a certain speed. That's the way we describe the world and
Heisenberg with the armature of quantum mechanics says you can't actually do that
You can't specify the location and the speed
Simultaneously of any object you can't do it according to the quantum equations
So the very language of reality that we used to use
No, they're applies. Why can't you measure both at the same time?
Well if you have a particle described as a wave, right?
And you want that particle to have a definite location that wave has to be highly
Spiked so that you can say ah almost a hundred percent likelihood it's at this location
But when you see how the notion of velocity comes into quantum mechanics
It has to do with the wave length of the wave and so if you want something to have a definite speed
It has to have a definite wavelength. That's not spiky. So to have definite location needs spiked have definite speed
You need wave those are different shapes and you can't have them at the same time and have the same time
Can I try analogy nowhere near as precise is what Brian just said
But sometimes I like this musical analogy if you play a chord
Which is a whole bunch of notes together you can play chords
But you can't simultaneously be playing a single note so the chord is like a superposition of the notes
And how this relates is that when you're in a precise
Location what Brian's describing is a sharp spike you're sort of in a superposition of velocities or momenta
So it's like it's like the the location is the note the
Velocities are the chords or vice versa. I know the velocity exactly and I'm playing chords. I'm no longer
Playing individual. I'm playing I can't isolate a single individual note in a superposition of notes
So what is so how does all this connect to the what they call the observer effect where you I want to measure the particle right there
I got a look at it so I shine light on it and the light sends it somewhere else
Yeah, so I can't actually ever know what the particle is doing right and so there's two things in there
One is as you're saying to look is to interact and
When you interact say by bouncing a photon off a particle you affect the particle because I need the photon to take the picture
That's right. So that's one key point that emerges from these ideas
But the other so we can never know anything no no
That's the crazy thing y'all went on this
Just not right
Quantum mechanics tells us that the things that you thought you could know are not the things that you can know
But with quantum mechanics we made predictions of the anomalous magnetic moment of the electron to 14 decimal places
It's the theoretical calculation and we measured it and it agrees decimal by decimal by decimal on all of those numbers
And that's why we love these numbers. They show us that we understand what we're doing
Okay, Brian so you can know without knowing is what you're saying
We can let me say this Brian the type of energy you're bringing
You are built for CNN this type of panel smoke
Fantastic yeah, all right, so this is so be in one of those street fighter squares
The decimal to the decimal to the yeah, it's great. This is great. This is good stuff. This is good television
so so go ahead now
So this this observe effect bring us home with certain has been widely
Miss
Applied by people thinking my consciousness is affecting yeah, look there is a big mystery at the heart of quantum mechanics
Even with our capacity to make calculations that agree with observations to the level of precision that I just emphasize
Perhaps with unnecessary theatricality there is there is a question that we don't know how to answer
Which is what you're asking when you observe you seem to be able to coax one result one answer even though the quantum
Description embodies many possibilities we don't understand how that happens is this the many world type of
It's it's one answer
But the Schrodinger equation is so beautiful and it does not actually include in it a way to understand how measurements are made
Yes, that's the key point and and so if you really take the Schrodinger equation very seriously
It simply says there are all of these possibilities and they're all have we don't have a theory of measurement
To get us through we still we are in the physics just you know
There are proposals people have put down mathematical equations that do answer this question
What is the many world type offices and many world's hypothesis is if you have a description of a quantum system like a particle and the quantum wave says
30% chance here 20% chance here 50% chance over here when you measure it you don't get only one result
There's one of you that finds it over here
There's another one of you that finds it over here and there's a third one of you that finds it over here
But these are all in different universes. Oh, it's 40
So you just invented multiple universes to explain something you can't otherwise explain the math invented it
Thank you, Jack. Wait, wait, wait, that's really important
So this guy named Hugh Everett 1957 in Princeton
He studies the math the very equation that Janimade reference to the Schrodinger equation
He says to himself let me take the math completely seriously and see where it takes me
And the math takes you when you look at the paper it's direct to this possibility of there being multiple universe
It's not made up it really emerges directly from an analysis of the equations and the equations make predictions that are confirmed
So you say maybe I should take this math fully seriously and that's where it takes you
So the passion with which Brian is describing this is like me explaining why I have glitter on my face when I come home
Because I was at an arts and crafts fair
Yeah
All right, we're gonna have to land this plane
So just briefly yeah, I know you spent your career doing this but just in 30 seconds explain strength theory
My god
20 seconds life have meaning go I only need 10. Oh look the old picture
Was at the fundamental constituents of matter were little dot-like particles the string ideas that maybe they're little extended
Filaments and why do we introduce this idea when you introduce this idea
Quantum mechanics and general relativity do play well in the sandbox
So
Okay, and that was less than 30 seconds. Whoa. All right. Okay. So what's what's in the future?
So I know astrophysically we don't know anything about dark matter
We don't think about dark energy. We shouldn't even name them because we don't know enough about them to even name them
And they should be called invisible I should did you call it?
You should be called Fred and Wilma
No bias
So or or faster in the light time travel time travel fast and light travel before the big bang is what you're working on or your peeps
Does it address any of this will quantum mechanics take us to all the places we need?
Yeah, I mean to zero evidence that quantum mechanics has any cracks whatsoever
It's the only theory that we've written down in the most successful
Successful theory and so we give you confidence to believe crazy stuff that it predicts exactly
And so we're pressing on and ultimately we think putting general relativity and quantum mechanics either because they're already born together
Or because they're blended together will be the key to answering these questions
We're not there yet, but that's exactly where we're headed and why do you need these extra dimensions?
Well, Brian was describing a string theory which may or may not be true
But string theory actually requires extra dimensions for it to make sense for the mathematics to allow gravity and
Matter and quantum mechanics to play nice together, but even without string theory the idea that their extra spatial dimensions
Is just kind of a natural extension when you start to think about space and time
And you start to take seriously Einstein's ideas
So now we're we're in the predicament where maybe those extra dimensions are harboring the dark energy
Maybe there's some explanation for the dark matter having to do with the extra dimensions
So now we can start to think of the extra dimensions as a dark sector
That are harboring really the resolution like we're observing them already
We just don't have the direct connection to be certain
So they're visible in plain sight
Yeah, I mean literally visible, but maybe dark energy is a consequence of quantum energies
Which is what paper Brian and I wrote many years ago
Dark energy dark energy which is driving the universe to expand ever faster
Which is something we observe
It is also driving my administration
I got a land this plane
I'll go on going
Well, just that we might be observing through something like dark energy
indirect evidence of extra dimensions we can't literally see into them
We can't point to them we can't move around in them yet, but we are living with the consequences
So these could be manifestations of these higher order phenomenon in the universe
Which is part of the motivation for thinking about them
Perfect sense
Thank you Chuck
I just wanted to put a button on that
Well from Einstein in his denial of quantum physics in spite of him contributing so mightily to the field
He you described the probabilistic nature especially from Shoridenger's equation
And Einstein said God does not play dice with the universe
And Niels Bohr retorted Einstein stop telling God what to do
You know you don't know if God needs to make some money real quick
You don't know that with the dice. Yeah, you know you got to see him down
Poppinies a new universe
I like how back in the day scientists threw shade at each other very poetically
The way they you know kind of shit posted was very the use of what we have good vocabulary
Yeah, great vivid language. They still do it the same today
Who I'm going to land this plane is offer you a cosmic perspective something
That I'm prone to do when we are exposed to this much information when I think of the 1920s
Uh
As a scientist it may be the most consequential decade ever
In the history of science
based on how it influenced our thought
Our the trajectory of our research that would follow and
But I want to make a slightly different point
Before the 1920s
What are scientists doing well doing sciencey things right
In a lab there's a chemical or there's a
Partic there's a material or a lymire flask
Yeah, yeah, flask. Thank you. Yes, you flesh out the picture of your lab. Okay
um
Suppose it was the 1920s and you had a friend relative
Or you were a politician and you heard that someone is working on the structure of
Adams and molecules
You'll say why does that matter to anyone?
I'm a carpenter. I just care that my wood atoms cut
Or that they can be shined or polished or painted
Why does that matter to me? I'm making cars and an assembly line
Why why does it matter to anybody?
You're taking your brilliant intellect and applying it to something that nobody cares about except your
cadre of people
But they will tell you well, it's the foundations of matter
And they'll tell you I don't care you're using up
National resources to do this
Well
What has happened every time we research the frontier of science
In basically every frontier of science
Whatever it looks like when you're doing it. It's easy to say that. I'll never apply to anything. I don't why are you doing that?
You wait a little while their clever engineers
clever other scientists
They see problems in the world and they see a possible solution
Do you realize today
There is no creation storage and retrieval
of digital information without an exploitation of the quantum
The IT revolution that is responsible for nearly half the GDP of the world at some level
Was birth in that decade at a time when people are just exploring the edge of our understanding of the world
Yeah, it would take 50 years longer than what is typical for an R&D project to show up as a household product
But all I can tell you is if you know anyone who says we're doing too much science or this science is not relevant to me
Well, I don't know why you're doing this that doesn't sound like it makes sense
What you're doing is you're cutting out at the kneecaps the legs of a future
Waves of discovery that could transform civilization not only take us to where we might want to go
But possibly solve problems that we it might have created for ourselves
So
There is nothing more shortsighted in this world than anybody running up and say we should do less science
Because every one of us in this room has been touched by it
And
And there's no greater demonstration of that than the science that unfolded in that decade the 1920s
That's the quantum side of it in the astrophysics side that births our understanding of the beginning of the universe and how the sun makes its energy
We would then learn how the stars manufacture elements in their core
We would learn take a few more decades
Exploiting the quantum applying to other realms of science
We would learn
That the very ingredients of our bodies
The carbon the oxygen the nitrogen the iron are traceable
To stars that underwent thermonuclear fusion following all the rules of quantum physics and those stars exploded
Scattered that enrichment across the galaxy
Creating the environment the chemical ingredients to make star systems with planets and on some of those planets life
So that that era
Not only gave us our IT revolution it gave us an awareness of ourselves that borders on the spiritual
And it's the fact that not only are we alive in this universe
Because of our ingredients are traceable to stars
The universe is alive within us
And that is a cosmic perspective
This
This has been dark talk
Live from the Beakman Theater
This is like a fifth time at the Beakman Theater
Fifth or sixth time and you guys have been a marvelous audience for us. We love you all. I and
Oh
And I but more than loving you all we love the support you give for science because there is no future
Of civilization without it we might as well just move back to the cave
So as always
Neil the grass Tyson here thanking our panel. I we got Chuck nice
Brian green
Channel 11
Hasan Minach
Neil the grass Tyson
You're a personal astrophysicist as always bidding you to
Keep little eight of you knew this
You can do it one more time come on
All right here we go. What's the tagline? Let me just
Now the other grass Tyson your personal astrophysicist bidding you to keep looking up keep looking up
Here we go remember it's he's gonna go you know grass hasn't done that and remember those eight people they cared
You guys all paid money
currency a real number that we know Brian know exactly how much you paid to those sharks at ticket master them now
He's gonna go Neil the grass has to keep and you go look in up here we go
Neil the grass Tyson your personal astrophysicist bidding you all to keep looking up all right
You