Pure life form on a pristine planet. What is the first question you would ask exploratory humans?
So first, let me say, go to an old episode of the Twilight Zone called The Invaders.
In that episode Agnes Morehead is this lone ranch woman on her little house in the prairie.
And you just have to watch that. It's called The Invaders. Point is, if I'm the other life form and I see humans,
my first question would be, have you come to colonize this planet?
Because if that's your goal, that's not happening.
This is Star Talk. Neil deGrasse Tyson here, your personal astrophysicist.
We did do cosmic queries today. Captain, I have Paul MacKurio, Paul.
What's up, my friend? Welcome back to Star Talk. Great to see you.
What'd you do with Chuck? What'd you do? What'd you do?
You know, he's in a bag somewhere.
Last time, Chuck, he was breathing. He was still breathing.
So how you been, man?
I'm good. I miss you. I miss you still doing the late show with...
Doing the late show with Michael Bear. I just had another appearance on that.
I've been touring with my Broadway show Permission to Speak, directed by Frank Oz.
Frank Oz? He's the voice of Yoda.
He's a man, as they say. He's a great, it's just a brilliant artist.
We love him. Yeah, he's been on our show. You'll find him in our archives.
He's amazing. And you'll see all the breadth and depth of all that he is.
Oh, the Muppet creator with Jim Henson, the Muppet creator, Miss Piggy and Fuzzy Bear,
directed everybody from Marlon Brando to Robert De Niro to me. I don't know what that's about.
He's really a stil-
What was that? I think he's living in a car by the river.
We love... So this is a grab bag.
There's a grab bag. We love these. I haven't seen them before.
If I don't know the answer, I'll just say I don't know.
Yeah, oh, you know. You always need answers.
No. Okay, here we go.
Eric Crosjado-T, Dr. Tyson in Duke,
Macuria. Wow.
And everyone called a Duke before.
Oh, because Chuck is called Lord.
Oh, Lord Knight.
Oh, I didn't. Oh, okay.
Okay, why have he got a title?
I'm a Duke now. There we go.
Oh, I hope that matters at home with my wife.
What are you, Duke of Earl?
I can't do it.
What do you do, Duke of Earl?
All right. They got Lord.
Duke, Duke.
Yo, you can do that. I can't do that.
I can't do Duke. Duke, Duke of Earl.
We're going to just do this for 30 minutes.
Duke of Earl.
And he got to come in high.
Give me some falsetto. Duke, Duke, Duke of Earl.
We'll find out what your Duke of Earl will come up with something.
All right, okay.
Greetings from Mangajila, Pennsylvania,
regarding the idea of time travel in star position.
Hypothetically, if I were to create a time machine,
it's time to go back to Mangajila 2,000 years ago,
what I not end up in empty space
because the entire solar system would not have arrived in that location
had I departed that I had departed from.
Every time machine is also a space machine.
There's space time machine.
They don't say it, but they have to be.
Why is that relevant?
Why does that matter?
They have to be.
Now, they got around that in back to the future,
because when Marty is trying to escape from the Libyan terrorists,
and he jumps in the DeLorean,
and he's quickly typing the date,
he typed 1955,
but it's the same day of the year as he leaves.
So he goes back to 1955,
Earth is in the same part of its orbit around the sun.
Because of the date.
The date was the same.
So they skirted.
But that can't be true because of the year.
Hang on. So they dodged that bullet a little bit.
Had it been six months earlier or later,
he just plopped in the vacuum of space, maybe dead.
So the reason why they dodged that bullet is because the entire solar system
is also orbiting the center of the galaxy.
Having to pick the exact date that was the key there.
Well, only for the moving coordinate system that is the solar system.
But because the whole solar system is moving,
he goes back 30 years, he's leaving our solar system today.
And if he only moved in time,
he would be where our solar system is today, 30 years ago.
But he also moved in.
Well ahead of where the solar system would have gotten,
the solar system would need another 30 years to catch up.
But he also moved in space as your point, not just in time.
Which is why he landed in exactly the same spot on Earth.
So it's implicit in the storytelling.
So you're absolutely right.
Nothing you can't do that in any way that makes sense.
But wait, if our solar system formed about 4.6 billion years ago,
isn't the premise part of his question has a false premise,
which is I would not end up in this because the entire solar system
would not have arrived in the location.
Solar system is there in that location.
No, no, no, no.
We are in a rotating galaxy.
The Milky Way is rotating.
And so that is all the stars in the Milky Way
are rotating around our central black hole in the center.
So if you go back in time,
if you go back in time,
you are no longer where you left in space.
And you'll be dropped in the middle of nowhere.
So you always have to land in a space time coordinate in the future.
We sort of do that, but without the relativity part,
if you're going to visit Mars,
you don't aim for where Mars is.
You aim for where Mars will be when you get there.
Then you intersect Mars.
So if you're going back 2000 years,
it will be an empty seat.
Well, there's going to be a home depot
because they existed in a subway sandwich shop.
They've been around.
In the mall.
They're franchising methodologies as brilliant.
And they never get enough credit.
What you need is,
you have to know where was the solar system
and the earth 2000 years ago.
And not only move back in time,
but move back to that location.
But you cannot say that the Manga Hila would not be the Manga Hila 2000 years ago.
Why wouldn't it be?
Why would not it be exactly what it is today?
The Manga Hila sounds like native tribe.
It is.
That's who would be there.
2000 years ago.
He's asking if I created time machine,
if I could go back to Manga Hila,
would I not end up in an empty space?
Yes.
He would unless he moved in time.
That's why I've been spending the last 10 minutes describing it.
I understand that.
So you answered his question.
Yes.
Unless he also moves back into space.
Space as well.
Correct.
Yeah.
Okay.
And
yes.
So every time machine is also a space machine.
Otherwise, it would be quite lethal.
Most of the time.
What would happen?
No, you're dropped into middle of space.
Because everything is moving.
You got to move with the action.
Okay.
Margo Lane.
If you were a life form on a pristine planet
watching exploratory humans arrive for the first time.
So you're observing humans arrive for the first time.
Yes.
What is the first question you'd ask them?
Assume you could understand each other.
And I have the answer to this.
My question would be,
really, you needed to sketch your shoes
where you don't have to bend over to put them on.
That's where you were.
That makes you so hard to see if you commercial.
That's where they forget about that.
That's where we are.
There's a species.
A lot of questions to Kardashians.
What?
Why?
Really?
What's up with that?
How do people who make Vaseline make any money?
Think about it.
I've had the same tub of Vaseline.
My Vaseline was handed down in the middle
by my grandfather in a will.
I don't think you want to understand
these conceptual...
Okay, here we go.
So I think people used to use Vaseline
before lotion was big.
I used it to grease the brakes on my car.
I still have a giant battery.
The tub of Vaseline are not as...
You know.
You could go through 30,000 bags of garbage.
You're not going to find one empty container of Vaseline.
All right.
So if you were a life form on a pristine planet
watching exploratory humans arrive,
what is the first question you would ask
exploratory humans?
Okay.
So first, let me say that you should look online,
maybe Pluto TV or one of these things that has old TV in it.
Meet TV?
Yeah, but there's several others as well.
Go to an old episode of the Twilight Zone
called The Invaders.
That's all I will say.
Why watch a lot of Twilight Zone?
Trying to remember which one that is.
So in that episode Agnes Morehead is this lone
ranch woman on a little house in the prairie.
And the whole...
It's a one woman show.
She's the only character in it.
And you just have to watch that.
It's called The Invaders.
Oh, I do remember this now.
Don't say anything about it.
Point is, if I'm the other life form and I see humans,
my first question would be just given
what I know about humans.
Have you come to colonize this point?
Because if that's your goal,
that's not happening.
We will not let that happen.
Okay?
Because we've seen what happens when you colonize stuff before.
Yeah.
Okay.
So that's the first point.
Second, that's interesting because
that implies that the humans
have more technology than the alien.
No, it doesn't.
Yeah, because all those aliens would have visited us first.
No, that's your...
Yeah, no, no.
No, no.
You're missing it.
The question you got to ask is
really you conveyed happiness by a little yellow circle
with a smiley face called an emoji.
Right?
There are so many bigger questions
that you could ask these people.
Yeah, that's true.
No, the colonization is a good point
because nothing good ever has really happened from that.
It's good and...
How about this?
I would say,
how did you survive yourself
wouldn't enough
to then come visit another planet?
That's what I would...
What you would do is you would be hiding behind something
and you'd say,
how do you feel about brothers?
You know, you got to ask the black question
because if they're not with the thing,
no, maybe you just say,
what part of the...
are you from?
Oh, I see.
We have a part of the demographic.
Well, if you see them go stepping down toward you,
you probably know if you're a Jew or a Black person.
You may want to let them just pass.
Or Gypsy's or Catholic's or...
Gypsy's or...
Yeah, yeah.
Or pretty much anybody.
Anyone non-arion.
Wouldn't you ask them how you got there,
though, seriously?
What was your technology that got you to watch?
I assume they would see them land in something.
No, no, but you'd want to learn from that.
As a scientist, I would compare notes.
And I would do things.
There's certain things that should be common between us
even if we don't otherwise...
What is this thing you call tang?
Like that kind of thing?
So, but how would I know that, though?
That's what I'm saying.
I don't know the tang or the Kardashians
or slip-on skitches.
I don't...
Unless he shows up drinking tang.
Do you have to ruin every joke and party with your stupid logic?
With a Kardashian underarm and slip-on skitcher.
Then I could ask, what's up with that?
Why can't you presume that this life form is smarter
and has the ability to see what we've been doing?
Here's what I would say.
I want to compare science notes.
Because science transcends time and space
in which culture does not.
But it doesn't transcend Instagram.
If you got a big following, it's all that matters.
So, if I verify that they can see
in the same wavelength as light that I can see,
they could have completely different senses.
Well, I was going to think, say, medically,
you'd probably want to check each other out, too, right?
Not first.
No, I don't mean that...
Start poking their bodies first.
No, I didn't mean it in that way.
What?
No, I'm not talking about anal probes or anything.
I'm just saying...
I knew thought of that.
I'll give the alien a bad name now.
No, I'm saying...
No, why wouldn't...
If you want to check out their mind
and compare notes in terms of science,
wouldn't you physically...
I would physically want to understand their bodies
versus vis-a-vis my vessel.
Their vers-vessel?
No, seriously.
If I were biologists, yes, but I'm a physicist.
So, no.
I'd compare...
I'd pull out a periodic table of the elements.
Because that organization is universal.
Anyone who knows the elements well enough,
as well as we do, would organize them that way.
Okay, but what if somebody that landed was like a
write a creative writing major and didn't care about science?
If they were the first emissary to another planet,
I'm pretty sure they would have given them some science.
Yeah, you're just a science snob.
Oh, only where the ones that everybody cares about.
Hello, Neil and Paul.
This is Julie and Ray.
Atlanta native writing from downtown Manhattan.
My question relates to stars in black holes.
I understand that our sun belongs to the third generation
of stars since the Big Bang.
Each star will eventually die out
in an explosion, some of which form black holes.
And then in eternal singularity of their mass,
is it possible that in the distant future
there will be more black holes than stars
since their lifespan is so much longer than that of a star?
Could the passage of time create a population of black holes
that outlive and nearly replace stars?
Yes.
Next question.
Okay.
That was a...
So, it turns out, according to Stephen Hawking,
black holes actually evaporate,
but very, very, very slowly.
So it's not burnout, it's evaporated.
It's a different...
Yeah, yeah, they wouldn't burn out.
Very, very, very slowly.
So there's a point where all the stars burn out
and they leave their corpses,
some of those corpses are black holes.
And they will come a time when the black hole...
black holes outnumber the living stars.
They will never outnumber the corpse.
But isn't the black hole then like...
It's like the Alice in the Brady Bunch
with a giant vacuum cleaner.
It's like sucking up all of the stars
that whether they evaporate or not.
I don't...
Alice in the Brady Bunch.
Yeah, the housekeeper.
Is that what she did?
She was...
She would back you.
The black holes?
Yeah.
I'm sorry, I can't connect.
I'm sorry.
But do you see...
Where was Alice in the grid of nine squares?
She was in the center.
And if you notice,
her image kept repeating back and forth.
Because it ended up taking off.
She was a pretty short loop.
Right.
And I got annoyed by it.
It's the same thing in the Mad Mad Mad Mad World.
Yeah.
I just saw it last night.
Really?
No, I'm serious.
Okay, I know every...
So there's the name of that movie.
Okay, so there's the shot when at the end,
Spencer Tracy is hanging onto the edge.
He slides down a cable and goes through a window
and is sitting there and a great dain is looking his face.
Yeah, and that to repeat it.
And it's a repeated and it was annoying me as well.
Ah!
I don't know how he got off on that.
But it's like, and he's doing this with his eyes,
move the same way.
But is it possible they're already more black holes
than stars in our universe?
No, because we know who the progenitor is of a black hole.
And it's a star that's made one out of 10,000 stars.
One in a million stars.
It's the most massive of stars as a black hole.
And in any volume of gas that creates stars,
it creates a lot of low-mass stars and fewer middle-mass stars
and very few high-mass stars.
So is this like a cosmic game of high-and-seek?
Well, it's called the initial mass function,
specifically.
And the initial mass function favors low-mass stars
and high-mass stars are just rare.
Rare.
And I don't know the latest iteration on the initial mass function,
but it's at least as rare as one in a thousand stars.
That what?
Are massive enough to make a black hole at the end of its life.
So all I'm saying is we have stars today that are born out of these
pockets of gas that are still alive and thriving
and we've only had one or two black holes.
So no, black holes do not outnumber stars.
By the way, they will outnumber stars in a trillion years,
the few trillion years, when the lowest mass stars burn out their fuel.
It sounds like stars need like a support group of black holes
in a way to get out with.
Now, that'll be fine.
Black holes need no support.
The more black holes that develop,
we're all in jeopardy, no?
I just avoid them, that's all.
Well, but what you do emotionally in your relationships
to other people is not what's relevant here.
Yeah, we just need a map of where all the black holes are
and then step around them.
That's...
Especially in your time machine.
You don't want your time machine to land in a black hole
because you didn't type in the right space time coordinate.
All right, let's move on.
I think we answered that thoroughly.
Seizard Fredique from Bogota, Columbia.
Love it.
Uh, Speed of Light.
See, shapes our reality and its fundamental properties.
However, it is intriguing to consider that
regardless of the unit used,
see could potentially be half double or any other value.
Could you suggest factors other than the possibility of it being an imposed
constraint within a simulation that might determine
the seemingly arbitrary value of this universal constant
as we understand it?
Wow.
Here's a couple of speed of light facts.
299 million, 792,440 meters per second.
Yes.
And do you know where the C comes from?
The Latin word speed?
C stands for constant.
Yeah, but do you think that there's a speculation
from a 1922 historian and scientist that's
it's salitrious.
The Latin for speed.
That's the first I've heard of that.
Well, that's why I'm here to open your horizon.
It's true.
First I've heard of that.
That doesn't mean it's not.
It's the most fundamental constant in the universe.
Right.
And the word constant begins with a C.
I understand.
So, but there's that obviously.
So, if I'm wrong,
I'd be intrigued to learn that that's what was really going on.
Okay.
It's not just an after the fact suggestion.
So, the units are arbitrary,
completely arbitrary.
You said you're, how tall you five nine?
Mm-hmm.
If I measured your height in units of five nine
this, then how tall you?
Those units, those number of units of five nine.
If I have a new unit that's five feet nine inches.
And I'm one unit.
You're one.
Okay.
So, your point being...
That doesn't make you shorter or tall or anything.
But your point because...
I'm saying that the units are arbitrary,
but the speed that we're measuring is not.
That is real and it's fundamental.
So, the units don't matter.
And so, precisely, do we understand the speed of light?
It's been measured so precisely
that it defines the length of the meter.
That's how well we know the speed of light.
So, if we get another pointer precision
in the measurement of the speed of light,
it affects the definition of the length of the meter.
So, you can vary that.
Well, only in the points where it's still uncertain, that's correct.
But it's the most amazing fundamental thing there is.
So, there is no inherent...
There cannot be any inherent uncertainty around the speed of light.
That's what you're saying.
Whatever uncertainty there is, it's smaller than our capacity to measure it.
Then how do you know that there is uncertainty if you can't measure it?
There is always uncertainty in every measurement.
How do we know that?
Always.
So, I'll tell you again.
Five nine.
Are you five nine in a quarter?
Are you five eight in three quarters?
Are you five eight in seven eighths?
Are you five nine in one eighths?
You five nine in one sixteenths?
How can you give it to me in units of inches?
You've approximated.
Haven't you?
Well, it depends on what sucks I'm wearing.
You have approximated it.
So, now I measure it five nine.
Let's say you're exactly five nine five feet nine inches.
What does that even mean?
The thickness of the line that's the nine inches above the five feet,
where are you within the thickness of that line?
Are you five eight and ninety nine one hundred seven inch?
Are you five nine and one one thousandth of an inch?
Are you saying exactitude is impossible?
Correct.
Oh, you can't agree where?
You can never measure something exactly.
Is that it because of the space time continuum?
No, it's what's called measurement errors.
But they're not errors.
They're just measurement uncertainties.
So, if you were once five eight and then you're later on five ten,
there was a point in your life where you were exactly five nine,
but you could have never measured it to be so.
Right.
All you could do is measure it and bracket it
according to the uncertainties of your measuring device.
Right now I'm exactly five nine.
I felt it.
It was a little vibration.
Little vibration.
So, measurements are never exact.
And they never can be.
And they never will be.
That's correct.
You can only know them with greater precision.
And your how tall?
At my tallest six two.
But you shrinking.
Yeah, I'm probably shrinking.
Is that your spine collapsing?
The discs between your spine and stomach.
Fluid.
Yeah, but you can go into space and grow in interso.
But your space suit that you walk in and the space walk
is made taller than the one you took off in.
Why are we growing?
Because gravity that...
Gravity's no longer squashing you.
So the atoms are getting strength.
Yeah, molecules.
The stress is out.
Right.
So, I'm probably six one and three quarters now, I guess.
You are, as they say in science, a tall drink of water.
All right, here we go.
Doesn't that mean you have great affection for me?
No, it's no bounds.
It's boundless.
All right, Stefan Summers.
This is from Heston, Kansas.
I was making my way through your old...
You're a small town.
I love it.
Yeah.
Okay.
Making my way through your old queries and found one
where you talked about how if we could pass through wormholes
then gravity would as well.
But my understanding is that gravity is the warping of space
and since a wormhole is making a hole
through the dimension of space would it be warped on the other side?
Furthermore, if a wormhole is a literal hole
through a dimension, would we be able to pass through it
or even perceive it as being...
as beings who live within our three-dimensional space?
Wow.
You know what it's...
That sounds like he wants to write another of the sequel to...
Does it...
Do you want me to repeat anything?
No, no, no, no.
He wants to write the sequel to interstellar.
That's what he's trying to do there.
Exactly.
So a wormhole uses...
If we were to make one, it uses negative gravity.
So we know how to make a wormhole.
We just don't have the substance to make it happen.
Gravity collapses space time on itself.
Negative gravity, if we could...
negative matter, would pry open space time.
It creates a shortcut through.
So if we did that,
we, in principle, should be able to position it in such a way
that pops a hole through the fabric of space and time.
And you step through and you're instantly on the other side.
Which, by the way, would have rendered
transporters completely obsolete in Star Trek?
Think about it.
Just stuff through a wormhole to get down to the planet.
Yeah, but there's no guarantee you're going to get through without getting lost.
It's like Google Maps and you take a right
and it's something you're in a quarantine situation.
I'll take that chance...
Because you don't pay attention to Google Maps.
I'll take that chance over
dematerializing my body into energy
and rematerializing it back into matter on the other side.
Why do you think that that's not possible?
Because you're like...
You know, it ends up on your...
I know.
Anything.
My thoughts, my memories,
stored in the synapses of my brain.
I don't know what's going to do that.
Maybe you could help.
Let's say you misplaced your keys all the time.
Suddenly things...
You can shake it up arranged.
You know, you can shake it up all the time.
That's a possibility.
But the brain is so complex,
I'm guessing that if you dematerialize it
and rematerialize it,
chances are you'll mess it up rather than improve it.
Okay, but if we're 3D and a wormhole is in another dimension,
how do we even know what's there?
It's like trying to change a flat,
knowing where the car is.
We see the part of the wormhole
that intersects our dimensionality.
But it's only part of the wormhole.
Well, so here's an example I gave
in another show.
If we live in a flat sheet of paper,
and then we just stand in a round
and we see a dot just appear out of nowhere,
then dot becomes a small circle,
and then a big circle,
which is watching this.
And then it shrinks back again,
becomes a dot and then disappears.
That'd be freaky.
No, that's called a Vegas Act.
It's a magician.
He works at the lounge.
Completely freaky.
Elijah.
What you just witnessed was a three-dimensional sphere
passing through the two dimensions of your world.
And you described it as a point,
and then circles that grew
until the circle was as wide as the diameter
of this sphere.
And then it went back and then disappeared
as it passed through to the other side.
So, higher-dimensional things passing
through our dimensionality will manifest
in some way or another.
So in answering this question,
then the answer is,
if a wormhole is a literal hole through a dimension,
will we be able to pass through it
or even perceive it as being,
as beings who live
within our three dimensions?
Yeah.
You can perceive it.
You would see the part of the wormhole
that intersected our dimensionality.
But nothing more than that.
You want to appreciate all of what also is going on there.
The fact that it moves into a fourth dimension,
you're not going to catch that.
But if you're passing through a wormhole,
you're going to instantly get to the other side.
Instantly.
So, movies like showing that you're going through this tunnel,
you know, it's like in the water park.
No, it's correctly done in Rick and Morty.
Which is exactly why I watch Rick and Morty
for my science knowledge.
And this dude, what's his name?
Dr. Strange.
Do you know what I'm talking about?
I would, if I had a super power,
I just would want to be able to do that.
It's a very sophisticated,
undistinguished state.
It's not this.
It's not trying too hard.
It's like,
Yeah, I mean, I prefer the Rick and Morty.
The wormholes because Rick uses real science.
And what is it about that wormhole and Rick and Morty
that's accurate to?
No, he just uses real science.
Whereas Dr. Strange uses magic.
If you can't pursue the wormhole,
aren't we in a way like walking through life like this?
Tourists that have lost the New York City
just looking up, taking pictures at everything?
Yes.
And isn't there a way that science can sort of make us
not feel that way?
Deal with it.
You can't become a scientist unless you are comfortable
being steeped in ignorance.
Okay, so we have this constant debate.
This is where you just like try to get off on
being lazy and not trying to get stuff right.
No, I want to get stuck right.
Oh, it's better to not know anything.
All right, let's go have a bottle of wine.
No, it's
learn to love the questions themselves.
Oh my God.
I went through law school.
I don't need this.
I'll just answer a freaking question.
Will you talk to you about science?
Like looking at Picasso and then you're like,
whoa, why is it nose on his calf?
I don't know.
And then some some historian, artist
already has a theory and they're completely full of,
you know what?
Okay, you know what you're fired from science.
I don't think he ever put his nose on his calf.
Yes, he did.
All right, here we go.
Oh, this is Captain Carl with two Ks, everybody.
Oh, hey, Captain Carl from St. Thomas.
US Virgin Islands.
I've often wondered as a photographer and as physics
enthusiast is our colorful world a result of our white star.
White being made up of all colors.
What if our planet or any planet was orbiting a blue or red star?
What our world be different shades of red or blue?
By the way, I just want to thank you, Neil, and shout out to your comedic sidekicks.
So would our worlds be different shades of red or blue
for orbiting a blue or red star?
With our current eyes, yes.
But if we evolve there, there's no reason why our evolutionary path
wouldn't have taken, divided up the blue light into different subcategories.
Yeah, but if you have pure red, then tire, it's going to feel like a brothel.
Yeah, however, don't pretend you don't know what that is.
The width of our sensitivity to light is much greater than any single band of light.
Say that again, you lost me.
All right, so you have Roy G. Biv.
Do you know Roy G. Biv?
You don't know Roy?
Red, RGL, green, blue, indigo, violet.
Roy G. Biv.
Okay.
You know, you never know.
No, I never know.
I learn something every day.
Yeah, it's why I'm here.
Okay.
Okay, Roy G. Biv, we see all those colors.
Now, when we make color photos
by Hubble or the James Webb telescope
in the infrared part of the spectrum,
you can't see colors in the infrared part of the spectrum.
So you know what we do?
We take RGB,
slap it onto different wavelengths in the infrared part of the spectrum
and create a color photograph out of it.
That's what you would see if our site was shifted
to the infrared part of the spectrum.
It's what the world would look like.
So the infrared part of the spectrum
is it neutral in color?
You can't detect it at all.
But if we evolved to see it,
there's no reason to think our brain wouldn't assign colors to it.
That's what's going on here.
We're assigning colors.
In fact, Richard Dawkins,
the evolution of biologist,
thinks that bats actually, when they echolocate,
they see in color
because their mammal brain has that capacity.
So why not use it?
So when you're using echolocation,
tag it with a color.
So if we ordered it,
if we ordered it a blue star,
we'd still have, would we still have clear skies?
In other words, every style...
If we have our eyes evolved
in this star,
and then transport us to a blue star,
then we would not see colors
in the blue because we can only see colors
in the visible part of the spectrum.
There'd be blue and ultraviolet.
We only see colors in the visible part of the spectrum.
However, you can
fake it,
authentically fake it.
That's called the perfect Instagram filter.
So going in that direction,
we have violet.
Take three bands in violet light.
They're adjacent to one another.
Then once you do that,
you assign RGB,
bring them back together,
and you can reconstruct
what you would see
if our sensitivity were shifted
to the violet and ultraviolet part of the spectrum,
to the blue part of the spectrum.
So we should think of it as shifted color
is what it is.
But we only limited in how much we can...
Our abilities shift.
We're very limited.
Well, you are.
I'm not.
So we see red through violet.
That's it.
If you want to see color anywhere else,
you take out the RGB,
slap it down on three different bands,
and out comes a color picture
of x-rays,
of infrared,
of ultraviolet,
of gamma rays,
all the above.
And so,
a red planet,
a blue planet,
a red star,
a blue star,
is there any star
with a color
that you have the ability
to see without sort of
slapping our...
That doing that technique.
RBG.
Yeah, RBG.
Right.
Say it.
Roy G Bid.
So no,
just the way we evolved,
we can't see into it.
So, by the way,
this band of visible light is very narrow
compared with ultraviolet or infrared.
Very narrow.
So,
we're practically blind no matter what.
And insects see into the deep
ultraviolet.
Insects.
And they're perfectly happy.
When I stare into a very bright light
and then I can't see for a second, what's happened?
That's a different thing.
You over stimulate the retinal cells
and they have to recover.
Yeah.
Which takes several seconds.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Which is always fun, by the way,
after you've been drinking.
All right, another question.
Hello, I'm John Mayhoy.
Mayhoy.
There you go.
And from Parkland, Florida.
I know that the Cosmic Mercury background is like a snapshot
of the early universe.
And its temperature has been dropping ever since.
So, I'm wondering, could this temperature be used
as a kind of universal clock?
If we could measure it super accurately,
would that tell us exactly how well the universe is right now?
Would that age be the same no matter what
where you are in the universe?
Yes.
Because every part of the universe was in the same place
at the same time, 13.8 billion years ago.
So, the oldest things in the universe
in every direction you look
are exactly the same age,
traceable to that period of time.
So, yeah, everything.
Now, at this moment,
we see in the past.
So, we can ask, what is that thing doing now?
Well, it's even farther away from us.
It's, and we can think of the diameter of the universe.
It's how big the universe is today, even though you can't see that.
And that diameter is coming in at 96, something like that,
billion miles, full diameter.
So, if you could see those galaxies out of horizon today,
that's what they look like.
But that would need an infinite speed of light.
And that's...
I'm not giving you that.
Why?
Not possible.
I'm not giving it to you.
Observational limits on the universe.
And temperatures the only way to measure this,
is to have a universal clock is temperature.
Temperature also works.
Yeah.
So, as the universe grows, the temperature cools.
So, it's a one-to-one correspondence.
So, you can just backstrapulate to the early universe.
So, there's a hard-to-serene.
And they do a forensic...
Why are you so morbid?
Well, because that's how my brain thinks.
And so, they get in it,
figure out based on the temperature of the body when the body died.
Yes.
So, that's what's happening there.
I hadn't thought about it that way, but that works.
Yeah, you got the crusty old cop,
and then you got the sexy sidekick.
That's right.
Maler Fee, man.
I hadn't thought about that.
Well, that's why I'm here.
What's the next question?
Okay.
This is Joe Lipparella from Pennsylvania.
Relativity tells us that as an object approaches a speed of light,
or is in a deep gravitation,
a well-timed slows to a stop relative to other observers.
My question is,
what is on the other side of that extreme?
If an object is motionless,
and if there is zero gravitational effect on it,
how would time work for that object?
If there's zero gravity,
then time goes fast for it.
Well, an object is motionless,
and if there's zero gravitational effect on it.
Right. So...
How would time work?
When you are in the presence of gravity, you age slower.
So this is like the ultimate anti-aging hack.
This is we should bottle this.
We should be on QVC right now,
not on this dog and pony show you called Star Talk.
We can be making some big stuff.
But start our own QVC channel.
Yeah.
Dr. Tyson's QVC hack.
So what are they asking then?
They're asking my question is,
what is on the other side of that extreme?
In other words,
Relativity tells us that as an object approaches a speed of light,
or is in a deep gravitational well, time slows to a stop.
Okay. So now watch.
So some years ago,
people realized you couldn't accelerate past the speed of light.
But does that preclude a particle existing faster than light?
If you can't accelerate past it,
can you exist on the other side?
And...
Sirius thought was given to that,
to the point where there's some movies based on it.
And there's a hypothetical particle that has these properties.
It's called a tacky on.
Tackyos from the Greek meaning fast.
Tackyos.
Tackyons.
And tackyons would live backwards in time.
How is that possible?
Because if time slows down as you reach the speed of light,
on the other side of speed of light,
if you continue the equations,
jumping that gap time would go backwards for it.
Tackyon.
For it.
For.
Yes.
Yeah.
For it.
Do we know they exist?
No, never found them.
So then how could you have a theory about something that you'd...
Because it's allowed to exist by Einstein's equations.
And if something is allowed,
that's good enough for you to go out and look for it.
If other parts...
But at one point do you stop looking and all serious and go,
when this doesn't...
But if you can't find it...
Welcome to the frontier of science.
No, it's like I can't find my phone in my house.
I'm not going to keep looking.
Go, I know it's there.
We don't know.
That's right.
It's a mystery.
But if you give up and someone else finds it a month later...
So would time meet an object with no gravity and no movement,
it's like my lazy good for nothing, 15-year-old son,
and won't move along.
Right? It just lays, just sits there.
So the answer to the question is,
yes, or is it that clear?
The answer is...
Well, wasn't there two parts of that?
Yeah, there's the...
An object approaches speed of lighters in a deep gravitational well.
Time slows to a stop.
Yes, in a deep gravitational well.
Yes, time slows.
Correct.
And what is on the other side of that extreme?
And that would be techy on.
Techy on, which we are known that we haven't found them.
Okay.
Correct.
Got it.
The techy on's work in the equations.
So as a result...
And so we're saying, well, right,
all these other ways, maybe this prediction of the equation should work as well.
Got it.
So if you are motionless in space,
for as you're concerned, you still have your own timeline,
and all that matters is what other people will say of you as they fly by you.
So everyone will have a different time reference for you.
But all you care about is your own clock and your own wristwatch and your own clock on the wall.
And that's all you care about.
Now, that's if you're not moving,
but if there's no gravity,
then time speeds up for you.
So if an object is motionless and there's zero gravitational effect,
how would time work for that object?
This is where we're talking...
And so this is where we were joking about gravity anti-aging hack, right?
So in other words,
there'd be no aging because time...
There's zero gravitational effect.
Yeah, but you...
And everyone else around you,
in your same reference frame,
will age at exactly the same rate.
It could be one second for every ten seconds outside of your club.
But it won't matter to any of you.
You can't hack that system and say,
I want to go back to when I was younger.
Okay, but if you're so smart, tell me who in that group is going to get a plastic surgery first
to avoid the aging process?
Yeah, plus if you're in space with zero G,
some surgeries aren't necessary.
No, well, you had straight...
Well, because you got nothing pulling on you.
But nothing pulling on you.
So the floats.
That's what we should invent.
We should invent people.
Zero G facial surgery.
I like this question.
It's very simple and straightforward, but interesting.
Dennis Alberti, please explain buoyancy.
buoyancy.
I love it.
All right, so it's all about density.
In the end of the day, it's about density.
And gravity, you know?
So if you are...
And gravity, yes.
If you are less dense than the medium you're immersed in,
you will float to the top.
Is that simple?
Is not more complicated than that.
Defined density.
Dancing.
It's how much matter you can cram into a certain volume.
So the big advance,
it's amazing this didn't happen until the 19th century.
Was there was some early variants in the 18th century,
but it really took off in the 19th century.
The fact that you could float metal.
If you make a boat out of metal,
then it's almost impervious to war.
Not icebergs.
And a billion dollar gross at the movies.
It's exactly what Titanic did.
But probably up to two or three billion now.
Look, to summarize it, a submarine is a boat in denial.
So here's what happens.
So...
You should react to that.
That was a good line.
So...
A submarine is a boat in denial.
So if you have a hull that's made of metal,
any bits of that metal would just sink to the bottom.
However, if it's in the hull shape,
it's pressing down on the water.
The water is rising up.
And you've created an environment that on average is less dense than water,
and so therefore it floats.
Because of the V shape.
Because most of the volume is air.
So you get to add the air plus the metal
as part of the contents that's within the volume.
And when you do that,
we systematically reduce the density of the material.
If you go back a thousand years ago,
people made boats out of wood,
sensibly because wood floats.
So you would make anything out of wood, it would float.
That made complete sense, but you were susceptible to attack.
But if I took a metal plank, a four by 12 piece of metal, flat,
and threw it in the water,
would that sink?
Yes.
Because you don't have that V shape,
you don't have the relation to air.
Because it's all about volume.
It's all about volume.
So if you carve it into a volume,
then it's the mass of the shell divided by the full volume of the whole thing.
And that gets very low to be lower than water.
It'll just float.
It's the same principle why an iceberg can float.
Because you've...
Icebergs are just simply less dense than water.
Simply less dense.
So you don't need that V shape for that to...
For an iceberg? No.
No.
I mean, you don't ever need a V shape, except that...
I mean, like Styrofoam will make the boat,
but it doesn't need a V shape.
V shapes are important if you know the material you're working with is heavier than
than the stuff itself.
Because you're displayed, you want to display.
Right.
It's all about displacement.
Correct.
So the bottom line is
icebergs float.
You got a V shape hull steel float.
Yes.
Styrofoam cooler.
Best scenario.
You can sit on it and tap in and get a couple of beers at the same time.
At the same time.
Okay, that's why I'm here.
Paul, I'm tapping one more.
One more.
He got it.
Okay, this is actually very interesting.
One, Terry Burke from St. Louis.
My question is simple.
Nuclear fission and fusion, a small amount of matter is lost and converted to a large amount of energy.
Is the gravity associated with the lost mass also lost?
No, because, great question, by the way,
gravity emanates not only from mass, but also from energy.
Because mass and energy are the same thing.
Different sides are the same coin.
So, you're not just losing mass and non-energy.
You're losing some combination of the two and they go hand in hand.
So, the answer is no.
Is the gravity associated with the lost?
No.
And that can never vary.
This is a constant.
This can never, the idea that gravity associated with the lost mass is also lost.
Oh, matter and energy are one and the same thing.
So, they each distort the fabric of space and time.
And that's all you need to know about it.
Okay.
We will commonly think of matter,
distorting space, but if there's energy there, it will distort space as well.
And equals empty squared reminds us that they're two sides of the same coin.
The more the amount of energy it's created is the same amount of gravity lost.
In other words, the mass lost is gravity associated with the lost mass is also lost.
Do you lose more gravity?
The more energy that's created?
If it leaves the system, yes, you're losing gravity anytime,
any matter and energy leaves the system.
No, I know, but doesn't it change over time?
No, you know, depending on the amount of energy that's created,
the more energy that created, the more gravity is lost.
No?
Yes.
But the, it's a lot of energy and a very small amount of mass.
So, I wouldn't lose sleep over it.
Well, listen, it's up to me what I lose sleep over.
Just because you walk through life not caring about science the way I do.
I can't.
It is weird, though, that humans for one third of a rotation of the earth are semi-comatos.
One last question.
I'll do it in somebody.
Quick one.
Okay, okay.
Okay.
Uh, uh, uh,
Mick Markler.
I used to have a bell here.
I don't know what I'd do with it.
I'm Mark from Portland, Oregon.
So, the system comprises of remnants from a single supernova
or a collection of many.
If many, I'm curious how are
or any galaxy diffuses multiple supernovas together.
Okay, so first, a supernova is a huge explosion
and it's gutsy just scattered everywhere.
Just start with that.
Then the galaxy rotates as we say,
differentially.
So the inner parts complete a circle faster than the outer parts.
This shears the gas clouds that have all been contaminated by the detritus
of a supernova explosion.
And you get a few rotations of the galaxy.
This stuff becomes very well mixed.
And the next generation of stars is going to have all the ingredients
from that last round of supernova explosions.
It was like fertile ground.
Yes.
It's the next round.
Yeah.
Got it.
All the way through.
All right, I think that's all our time.
Good questions.
Wow.
Yeah, excellent.
All Patreon members.
But this is for our general audience.
General audience.
The week, by the way, if you join Patreon,
we do special custom Q&A sessions just for you.
And that's on the other side of the Patreon paywall.
Yeah, and it's worth paying because we dress up as a Lidavithan characters
when we do that.
That's the cutest.
So but yet that's what you're missing because you're too cheap to join.
All right.
Good for you.
Oh, and we give out gold bars to everybody.
That's when I put the sword and that sword, you see, I gotta use that sword.
Right.
And every Patreon member gets a puppy.
An opponent.
All right, we're done here.
Yet another installment of cosmic queries with Paul McEureo.
Paul, I'll find you your show on the road.
Yeah, PaulMicuryo.com.
Did someone say take that show on the road?
And that's what you did.
I did it in New York and then the authorities called and said,
inside out with Paul McEureo and my podcast.
Is there a movie called Inside Out?
There is, but thanks for bringing that up.
This is how you help me get people come.
Oh, yeah, you just copied something.
So don't go see it.
Yeah, inside out.
It has a good interactions with the audience.
You're very good on your feet in that way.
Yeah, my show permission to speak is about sort of engaging the audience
in their stories.
It was born out of crowd work at the audience.
Yeah, good.
Love crowd audiences.
But it's, but people have had your podcast.
Inside out with Paul McEureo.
Which I've been on.
You've been on in Paul McCartney and Stephen Colbert and a lot of fun people.
Well, I wasn't enough to
do you work?
The only reason Paul McCartney did it is because he found out you did it.
Oh, I think that's what I was.
And, uh, and he knows a lot more about the theory of relativity than you do.
Weird.
I don't know because I just already played music.
No.
Yeah, so hopefully people can check all that stuff out.
Paul McCurriot.
Yeah, but for it, you got it.
All right, this has been start talk.
Cosmacqueries, grab bag edition.
Neil the Grass Tyson here.
Thanking Paul McCurriot.
As always, I bid you to keep looking up.