You got to word here, assemblodes. Yes. That sounds like somebody just made that.
Once we figured out how to make some of this brain region, putting them together,
essentially was unleashing like new forces of self-organization, which is really what the brain does.
I mean, the brain builds itself at the end of the day. Very often when we do this experiment in the
dish, you better know like the instructions and provide them at the right time. You don't start
building a new house until you really have a very clear plan and the tools. In biology actually,
you know, cells come with the instructions. That's what we call this process, self-organization.
So if you were around in Frankenstein's day, Frankenstein would have just been a regular
joke on the street. Yeah. Hey Ben, hey, what's going on?
This is Star Talk, the old grass-tice in your personal astrophysicist. And today it's going to be
special edition, which means we got Gary or Riley Gary. Right, man. Yeah. It was good to have you.
That's just mine. Very good. And Chuckie, baby. Hey, man. All right. Not good to have me, I guess.
Okay. Okay. Good to have you. Gary, always good to have you and and Chuck.
So you got a word here, assemblodes. Yes. That sounds like somebody just made that.
Just assembled it. Yeah. assemblodes. Well, this is a show on assemblodes. What can you tell us about it?
All right. Not that long ago, we did a show on synthetic biological intelligence or if you
prefer, organized intelligence, organized. Yes. I remember. Right. Now, and those are, if I remember,
like 3D cultures to build brain-like structures for bio-computing. Right. So that's what that was
being used for. For our future overlords. All right. So this was putting biology onto technology.
This is something different. However, it's based around the organite in terms of, but this now becomes
organized assembling together. Oh, now that then, self-organizing, organized. So I'll guess today.
So we just, okay, we'll get an answer with, baby. What could go wrong? Let's not do that question,
just. Okay. I'll say that for the end. Yeah. Okay. Go. So I'll guess today. I had the great idea of
trying to get these organoids to work together and coined the phrase, assemblodes. So
assemblodes is down to our guesswork. Now, these assemblodes can help us uncover the biological
mysteries of our own mind. So are we just clumps of cells in the big petri dish we can call life?
Yes. I think sometimes, speak for yourself. Sometimes it can feel like that. So let's find our guess.
Say in a petri dish of life. Yes. That was beautiful. Well, you're welcome. I'm just reading it. And
so let's, let's see what mysteries have been sold. What mysteries are still out there. And our
guess now. So dropping on our guest. Yes. Please. So we have Sergio Paska. Sergio, welcome to
Star Talk. It was great to be here. Thank you so much for having me. Yeah. So you're a neuroscientist
on Star Talk special edition. We love neuroscientists because that there's a serious future
opening up right before our eyes. Yes, it is. In plain in plain sight. A fresh frontier.
Fresh frontier. A stem cell biologist. Stem cells have been pretty much in the news on and off.
Yeah. A couple of decades. Yeah. Professor psychiatry and behavioral sciences at Stanford. When I
think about this, however, I think of a psychiatrist or behavioral scientist, they're just putting
someone in a couch who are observing their behavior. This sounds way more invasive. What
is your doing? It sounds very puppeteerish. Exactly. And you've also been tending. That's good.
So we can dig you up in the Ted archives. Correct. Yeah. Excellent. And here in 2023, you made a
night of the order of merit of Romania. Oh, all right. So let's get back to basics here and put
us on the same page with what an organoid is. So an organoid is a clump of cells that is cultured
in a dish in a three-dimensional structure. And the name actually organoid, which is organ-like,
is supposed to suggest that it resembles an organ. So it's similar in some function. Of course,
it's not a replica of an organ, but is supposed to model features of an organ.
This is so in the case of a scaffold of an organ. I guess like parts of an organ or like parts
of the function of an organ. So for instance, for the brain, it's not really a brain in miniature.
It's not the entire organ in miniature, but it would be like parts or aspects of the brain
that are being modeled. And by the way, asteroids, they show up as stars on a photo because they're so
tiny, but they're not stars. So that they're asteroids. So it's organ-like, I guess the same
as you like star-like. Oh, wait. So those are organoids. Yes. All right. And so now, so now you
organize them in some way, or do they self-organize? You give them instructions that they follow?
Well, I guess all of this work to be honest, like, started with the ability to actually even
grow stem cells in a dish. If you were to, like, step back and think like how this all came
together, you know, stem cells, as you know, generally are derived, you know, from an embryo.
And that has been certainly like very difficult to do studies. But then about-
We're certainly politically fraught with issues related to the ethics of using human embryos.
Right. And that was a big issue until you guys figured out where your people figured out how to
create stem cells without a regular cell, the out of regular cells. So this is-
Well, that happened 20 years ago, almost almost 20 years ago, 19 years ago, when a Japanese
scientist, Shiniya Yamannaka made this like breakthrough discovery, where he actually showed that
you could actually turn any cell that we have in our body, but it's already differentiated.
So like back in time to look like those embryonic stem cells. And so almost like a,
you know, so like cellular alchemy, so to speak, right? Because it was like, we always thought that
it's a one-way street development is a one-way street. You never so like go back.
Just to run the same page, stem cells, while it's always in the news, just as a reminder
to the nonbiologist, it is a kind of cell that you, under the right conditions, can turn into
any other cell of the human body. Is that correct? Exactly. Yeah. It has nerve cells, muscle cells,
and that's why they're prevalent in the embryo because the embryo is manufacturing the-
Of the cells.
The cells.
Right.
Exactly.
Gotcha.
The stem cells have two properties. They can turn into any other cells and they can renew
themselves. So they can stay as stem cells for a very long time. And of course, there are multiple
levels of stem cells. The first ones are the ones that are the most powerful. They can turn to
everything. And then as you progress in development, they become more and more restricted in what they
can do. But the ones that are really in the beginning are the ones that you would like to have so
that you can ultimately guide them to become different other cells and tissues in the body.
So you put them in a time machine. Is that that box that's sitting behind you?
You say that. But how is that possible? How are you able to take a brain cell that you've
cultured and dial it back to a stem cell and then bring it into whichever area you need to
bring it to? So it was really a brilliant idea. The build on work that was done before.
Essentially, the experiment was very simply done. He just looked at the main genes that are express
in the stem cells. And then he said, let's see which ones are really important. So he took them
and he put them in a actually in the skin cell, took a skin cell and starting putting various
combinations of those genes that are very strongly present in those stem cells. And through this
combinatorial experiment, he found out for that if you put at the same time, pretty much confused
the cell, so to speak, and the cell becomes reprogrammed. That's what we call it cell reprogramming.
Because the cell is really reprogrammed to that state and it turns out that they have all the
properties of those embryonic stem cells. But you can make them from anybody in a non-invasive way.
And of course, you can store them, you can ship them to others. And so that was really a breakthrough
for the field because that opened up the possibility for the first time that you could get stem cells
from anybody from any patient and then start to study it in addition. I was finishing my clinical
training around that time and really to a large extent dropped everything because my expertise,
I'm a physician by training my expertise is actually autism spectrum disorders and neurodevelopmental
conditions. And I was incredibly frustrated by the lack of models to study disease.
We, there are animal models, but what is an animal model of autism? That has been to a challenging
aspect. We can't really access the human brain. That is sort of the, this curse, this unbearable
inaccessibility of the human brain. I mean, it's behind the skull and unlike any other organ,
you can't just go there, get a biopsy and study it. So we were sort of like blocked, so to speak,
blocked into this state where we couldn't really make progress. And yeah, so about 16,
17 years ago, I came to Stanford, mesmerized by the potential of this stem cells that we can make,
which we called induced pluripotent stem cells. And then started thinking, could we actually
turn them into neurons from patients and then study whatever defects are characteristic of
that disease, but outside of the human body. And that's really what enabled all of this. And
initially, that blew up in the whole field at that point. Exactly. The open all field. And in the
beginning, just to make it clear, it was, I mean, I got all the grants and all the fellowships
rejected all the time as this being absolutely insane. How can you actually make neurons in the
dish? And then even expect to find something from a disease that is so mysterious, right? Think
about, I mean, autism is a complex disease of social behavior. What are you going to see actually in
the dish? So I mean, we'll get back probably to this conversation, but it was actually key for us
to focus on a disease where we actually like knew what to expect, sort of like to calibrate. And
that sort of like started that, you know, this entire journey. And in the beginning,
most of these experiments were very simple. You know, you would take the stem cells from patients
that we derive in a dish and then kind of like spike in various molecules in a dish. So like
guide them to try to become neurons. And those differentiation experiments were like easy. But then
about 10 years ago, it became clear that we're going to need more of the three-dimensional aspect
of development to really capture even more complex features of the brain. And that's how some of
these three cultures, which are now known as organoids appear first. So if the neurons are so
organizing, how do they know that they're self-organizing and how do they know where to go and be
organized? That's a very good question. And, you know, I mean, self-organization is a remarkable
force of nature and biology, right? And very often when we do this experiments in a dish, to be
honest, for very long time, I was still like thinking like an engineer in the says that all if you
want to build something in a dish, let's say a circuit, you know, you better so like know the
blueprint, you better know like the instructions and provide them at the right time. And so you don't
start building a new house until you really have a very clear plan into tools. But what we realize
with time is that in biology, actually, you know, cells come with the instructions, you know, so once
you make a specific cell, they'll actually come with the instruction. And then by connecting, let's
say to another cell, it reveals another set of instructions. Right. And another one and another
one. And that's what we call this process self-organization. So which really is the formation of
or the structure from, you know, relatively homogenous elements, which which by the way, like talking
of physics and chemistry, this was known from the 19th century. I mean, there are classic experiments
that show, you know, that molecules organize quite beautifully, you know, the Riley Bernard
convection, I guess is the classic example. But biology just brings it to the next level. And now
organize the cells pretty much on their own. So what you're doing is you're bringing these
together in this culture, this 3D culture, where the message and directions are already resident
inside of the cell. So when you put them together or group them, they basically do what they
were going to do anyway. Exactly. Okay. With with with we want detail, which is we have to make the
parts right. If you don't have the right parts, then of course they won't know what to do. What to
do? Actually, what we spend a lot of time generally is making the part. Let's think about the human
brain. I mean, the reason why the human brain is remarkable is because it has all these parts,
which are very different. You know, unlike, let's say, the liver, the liver is relatively homogenous,
right? A few cell types can like any part is like any other. You look at the brain and now you have
thousands of cell types. I mean, the recent estimates, you know, say that they're probably
2000 cell types just in the human brain, right? Scatter through this nuclei and regions.
And the remarkable abilities of the brain really result from the cells interacting with each other.
So in the early days, like you know, 15 years ago, we were making just a few cells,
like a few spinal cord neuron cells or maybe a few cortical neurons. But then we've never really
leveraged the ability of the cells to connect with each other. And so that's where essentially
a sample, it's came where once we figure out how to make some of the cell types, some of these
brain regions, putting them together, essentially, you know, was unleashing like new forces of self-organization,
which is really what the brain does. I mean, the brain builds itself at the end of the day. You
know, if you think about it, right? And it reorganizes itself. Like if you damage a part of your brain,
it will reorganize itself so that that function might be taken up someplace else.
At least early in development. Yes. Early in development, it will do so. And then the more you
progress, the, you know, the less you can use that. The less that happens, right? What if you leave
your culture brain cells in the dish for nine months a year? What happens to them?
Do they just take care of business on their own or that they just fade away? Something crawls out
of the piece you're dashing. You have the smartest dish in the world. It'll chase you down the car.
Get that fork away from me. Well, that was something actually, you know, really fascinating
that we discovered like, you know, almost 10 years ago. So at one point, we were, you know,
my lab was still like in the early days. And at one point, you know, we realized that,
well, I mean, at this our expensive experiments, you have to keep feeding the cells and I was running
out of money in the lab. And so I told everybody in the lab, I said, you better go and your incubators.
And like make sure that you're not maintaining cultures that we don't need. We need to focus.
We need to save money. And then somebody in the lab comes and says, oh, should I also like remove
the ones that are like 300 days old? I was like, what do you mean 300 days old? It's like, yeah, I mean,
you know, I knew that we were keeping them for very long periods of time, but I had no idea that
we could keep them for such a long period of time. And it turns out that once you make this
cluster of cells and, you know, so like, I wish I could show you, I wish you were here in the lab
and I could show you, and maybe I can try, but they look something like this.
All right. I see it. You see it. Not there a lot. They're still like fixed, you see? So they're like
relatively large clumps of cells. They're floating in the media in the incubators. You
keep going and change media. And then at one point, we realized we can keep them for very
long periods of time. In fact, we maintain now the longest cultures that have ever been reported.
Like you can keep them for years. And so now the question was, are they stuck in development?
Are they progressing in development? And through a series of papers, we discover something
really fascinating is like, they actually keep track of time really well. So well that once they
actually arrive at about nine months of keeping them in a dish, they actually transition in terms
of their gene expression and some of the properties of the cells to a postnatal brain. So it's almost
like they know that birth should happen. There's almost until like, we think that there is some sort of
internal clock that keeps track of time. Is this the brain clock that I've read about? Yeah, this is
the brain clock exactly. I'm fascinated now that these cells have the ability to understand
basically a calendar. I mean, because they're not not observing the the sun going across the
sky a day and a night. Yeah. So what's what's what's doing the taking? Exactly. So I mean, you may
think that this is, you know, surprising. But if you think about it, it's not that surprising. I mean,
every time you make a human, you always make it in like 280 days. And here's the interesting thing.
If you take mouse stem cells, okay, or we have like chimp stem cells and you differentiate them
the same way in a dish, they'll finish development in their own time. But in that that same time period
reflects the justation period of a chimp. Like it will be three weeks for the rat. And it will be like,
you know, whatever is for. So this is, I mean, evolution has actually selected, you know, very well
like this periods of development. And so they're intrinsic to the cells. I think what we what was
surprising for us was that this happens also outside of the of the body, right? Outside of the
uterus. Of course, this is not to say that all aspects of development are recapitulated. I mean,
there are all kinds of things that are coming, right? What kind of information is that are coming
that are shaping development that we know that the more you invest in human brain development,
the more the environment is important, like sensory information, right? Like cognitive development
think about motor behavior afterwards. But especially at early stages of development,
everything is quite well regimented and goes according to a calendar. Nobody knows what the clock is.
So nobody knows what the molecular mechanism of it is. But it is somewhere in the cells,
it's something that is counting somehow time and that's why it's such a great time to do neuroscience.
Like more people should like come and do that. So where do these cells derive their energy from?
Because it's not you talk about a clock. There's not a battery in the back. What is powering this?
Because they're outside of the outside of the body. They've not got the whole human system to back it up.
So we feed them. So like a soup of chemicals that is made sort of like in the lab. So we like,
we provide them glucose, right? I mean, they need glucose and some of the amino acids and we give them
lipids, right? And so they need fats. And so we just like have we call them cell culture media.
And how do you measure if and when they are expressing their prescribed function? Because
a neuron has a very specific function. Absolutely. How do you know that they are actually
expressing that function? So we do all kinds of things. Like first of all, we just look to see very
often, you know, cells, I mean, not very often all the time cells have a signature. You know,
they express a certain combination of genes. So generally the first question is if you think you've
made a cortical neuron, let's say a neuron from the outer layer of the brain, how do you know that
it's a cortical neuron? Well, first of all, you kind of like look at what genes it expresses and you
compare it with what we know from a neuron in the actual brain. Then you can look at how it looks.
They're often neurons in the cortex have to like a pyramidal shape. We call them pyramidal neurons.
So you look, do they look pyramidal? That means like a pyramid? Yeah, exactly.
Pyramid dental. Okay. For me, pyramidal. Yeah. They really look like a tiny pyramid.
Okay. Yeah, an inverted pyramid. Like that's how they stood in the cortex. So you look at this
like the shape of the cell body or the other thing is sometimes they move in very specific ways.
And that's actually how the first assemblots were actually looking at how cells are moving. So here,
here's this interesting fact. You know, you may think that you know, you have all the cell types in
the brain, right? But they're all made, you know, when you build the brain, they're all made so
like in their place and then they sit there. Actually, it's more, and you know, a rule rather than an
exception that cells do not reside in the place in which they're born in the brain. So there's a lot
of movement. So think about the cortex, okay? Like the outer layer of the brain. It has neurons,
they're exciting other neurons and it has neurons there inhibiting other neurons. And there is a
very good balance between the two of them. Too much excitation you get epilepsy, right? So,
you know, think about that. No, here's the interesting thing. All the excitatory neurons are born there
in the cortex, but all the neurons that are inhibitory are built in a deep part of the brain. And
literally during brain development, they start moving, crawling for inches and for many, many months,
until they arrive into the cortex and then they kind of establish that balance. So in order for
you to build that cortex, it's not enough just to make the excitatory cells. You have to make the
inhibitor cells. And then the question is, how do they come together? How do they assemble? Because
that's where the name assembly it came. And essentially, the vision was like almost, you know, 12 years
ago was let's make this two parts of the brain, the one that makes the excitatory neurons and the
one that makes the inhibitor neurons and then just put them close to each other. And hopefully the
cells will know what to do because we certainly don't know how to guide them to do more. And it turns
out that exactly what they do, you put them together and this garbageic cells immediately start like
they have this processes, the cellar processes, they start to like smelling where the cortex is
and they literally start jumping. You know, you see the cells, they literally spend three hours,
they look in that direction and then they make a jump 40 microns. Then they wait for another three
hours. Kind of like smell where the cortex is, make another jump. And this process has never really been
seen in humans. This happens in the third trimester of life. But this is this is what's going on in
every developing human being. So professor, what you're saying is basically we have a bunch of cells
that are in a field and they they're looking and they recognize one another and then they just
start running to each other and slow motion. Pretty much, pretty much because they really come with
instructions of how to do this. And I think that's what happens in development. And that's why you build
the brain. I mean, our brains may be a little bit different from each other. But in the grand scheme
of things, they're quite the same. I mean, we have the same structures is not like, you know, you
have a thalamus in the spinal cord, right? We all have pretty much in the same position. So in order
for, you know, the brain to build itself that way, there are these remarkable forces that
bring all the cells together over and over again, every time you build a human brain. Wow.
Okay, this is the last thing I'm sorry. I know we got to move on to the next subject. But here's
what is like percolating in the brain right now. Is this once you kind of
perfect this technology? Would you be able to then introduce these cells and have them go in and
let's say for instance, repair a part of my brain that kind of makes me so stupid. I don't believe in
climate change or something. Well, we're sort of like a self assembly actually works really well
early development in the sense that all the cells are open to like connecting with the others.
But then it turns out that the as you progress in development, the cells become less and less
permissive. We don't have cells moving in our brain right now. Okay. You know, it's just not very
adeptive. So the challenge is that if you start to add the cells into an adult, like those circuits
are already formed. So it's not that easy. You know, um, to the dumbass circuitry, the dumbass circuit
is fully formed and very, very strong. Right. However, if you're able prenatal to identify brain
disorders or any disorder in a child, you might be able during the gestation process to go in and
and make changes. Exactly. And that's exactly what we're actually even early after birth because
the human brain develops for like years, even after we're born. That's amazing. So if Professor,
that that's amazing. All right. So Professor, you did some work and some research with cells
and you said you worked with autism patients and the like. And there's something called Timothy
syndrome, which is autism and epilepsy, which seems a terrible combination to a terrible
epithemathy. Yeah. But you then afflicted cells with this Timothy syndrome. Is that correct?
Yeah. And then reverse engineer it. How you could find a way to work with and do basically what
you said, take that away. Right. Is that could, I mean, I'm explaining that at all well, but
you probably could do it better than I. Yeah. If you would. So I mean, this, this goes back to like,
you know, the previous point when we were talking about how these stem cells were so like
discovered and what their potential was. So the question was if you really want to model a disease,
you want to model a complex disease such as autism and epilepsy, you know, where do you actually
start? I mean, psychiatric disorders are mysterious. These are, we still don't know how like this,
you know, thoughts and this complex social behavior rises in the brain. So actually, we thought we
would start with genetics because one thing that we do know about many of these developmental
disorders is that they're caused by mutations. They're caused by very severe mutations.
All right. Right. So there's this rare, rare syndrome. I mean, literally, we found about
3040 patients in the English speaking world today. Very few, but they have a mutation,
the spations in a protein that is actually a channel for calcium in the cells. Every time a neuron
communicates with another neuron, it opens up this channels. Let's calcium in and it essentially
translates electrical information into chemical information inside the cell. So it turns out that
these patients have one single letter mutation in their entire genome, one single letter that makes
this channel open for a little bit longer. That's it. And it's not all the time open. It's not,
you know, just slightly longer. So the idea was that if you were to model this disease, you could
make neurons from these patients, then look at them and actually monitor calcium inside the cells.
And if we were to see more calcium, it means that we started modeling the disease. And that's
exactly what we did because we wanted to really ascertain that we were really studying a disease
process that is relevant. So if you know the actual letter and when you're talking about that,
you're talking about the DNA sequencing. So if you know the actual letter, why not do something
like CRISPR where you just go in and snip out the letter? Well, sadly, you would have to change it
everywhere in the brain. And that is not, you know, doable to me. Okay. And this patients are very
severely affected. I mean, they'll have epilepsy, they'll have autism spectrum disorder.
They have a heart problem. So many of them would die because of a heart problem. And so that's
that's where we started with with cells from these patients. And then with this model that I've
told you now for the past 15 years, we kept building the models to be more complex and try to
understand these disease. And first went to study how calcium gets into the cells. Then we saw that
the cells are not moving right. They're not connecting property. And about three years ago,
which is, you know, one of the most interesting, you know, times in, in sort of like my academic life
was at one point, we just accumulated enough information about the disease that essentially the
therapeutic just became self evident, so to speak. You're just like, look at it and they're saying,
oh, this makes sense. This is what we need to do. And so I don't want to go into the details of how
we didn't does, but it has to do with how this gene is processed inside the cells with done a screen
and essentially identify a tiny piece of a nucleic acid that if you add to cells, goes right into them,
changes the channel and essentially restores almost every single defect that we've discovered over
the past 15 years. It's like within, you know, a couple of days. This is insane. I know,
but what you're talking about, he's a Sherlock County. This is just real detective work. I mean,
to work out that that is exactly what's necessary. I mean, you said it was obvious, but obviously,
it wasn't. Otherwise, someone would have seen it a long time ago. So if you were around a Frankenstein's
day, Frankenstein would have just been a regular Joe on the street. Yeah, he would have walked out
instead of like, he'd been like, hey, what's going on? Hey, that's feeling.
Are you mapping this with sort of an AI technology? I mean, that CRISPR's one pool, but there are
others out there. Is that what it is? Or is this just the empirical evidence from experiment?
It's a large empirical. I mean, we just, you know, just accumulate enough information about
the biology that at one point, it became clear. And it's quite interesting if you think about it,
because this is could be the first psychiatric disease that has been exclusively understood
with this human stem cell models, meaning by studying it, by studying human brain cells outside
of the body of those patients. Right. And so of course, the question is like, how do you actually,
you know, know that it would work? You know, generally what we do is we use an animal model for the
disease, right? You have an animal model, you have a mouse that has the same mutation, or turns out
that if you do this mutation in a mouse, it doesn't really recapitulate aspects of disease. It
doesn't work that well. So now what do you do? You can also just go straight into a patient. You
want to make sure that sort of like, it works sort of like in an in vivo setting. And so that's why
one of the things that we've done over the past years is actually also develop transplantation methods,
meaning that while the organics and the assemblies that we've been building are rather complex,
they still don't receive sensory input. They don't mature to the same level. So what we started
doing is actually transplanting them, meaning we essentially take the organ that we've made in a
dish, but now we put it into the brain over rat. And then if you do it early in development,
then the rat can actually grow to have about a third of a hemisphere to be made out of human cells.
You can literally see it on an MRI. And you may think, well, this is, you know, why would you even
do that experiment? Well, the reason is because now we actually have human tissue from patients
in a living organism. And you can test the drug. So what we did is we took the drug that we
tested in vitro in a dish, but then injected it into the rat the way he would do into a patient.
But then we looked at the effect on human cells, making sure that it doesn't kill human cells,
whether it doesn't do something else. So that is like one way that allows us actually
to test their putics in a way that is like safe, essentially. So the thing is if you want to
solve the issues of complex brain disorders, you're going to need more complex
assemblots. Now you've taken this assembly up a notch, have you not, and Daisy chained four
organoids together, but then gone down the path of sensory. If you could sort of expand on that
for us, because I think this is absolutely fascinating. You tell me they have feelings.
Is this what you're telling me? No. Yeah, the professor explained. No, you know, I mean, it turns out
that if you if you think about like brain disorders, you know, some of them are sort of like
hardware defects, right? I mean, parts are just missing. Think about in a stroke, right? You like,
you know, you lose like parts of the cortex. But most disorders that we consider today psychiatric,
autism, schizophrenia, we think of them more as like disorders of software of communication
between the cells. So it becomes really clear that if you really want to capture those processes
outside of the human body, we still like need to reconstruct those circuits outside.
And so this started like, you know, maybe five, six years ago when we thought, could we actually
build a circuit that is actually has an output, you know, really easy to measure? So we decided to
reconstruct the cortical spinal pathway. So that means and you know, this really well, everybody
knows this is like biology textbook information. You have a neuron in the cortex that generally
goes all the way to the spinal cord makes a connection or a synapse with the spinal cord neuron
and that spinal cord neuron goes to muscle. You have essentially three neurons, two connections.
You stimulate the cortical neuron information goes down to the spinal cord to the muscle, the muscle
contracts. Right. You know, it's as easy as so like text to biology. So we thought, could we
actually reconstruct this? You may think that it's easy, but here is is we don't know how the cells
find each other in development. By the way, we have no ideas about the rules. So what we did is we made
an organoid that resembles the cortex, one that resembles the spinal cord and then we made a ball
of human muscle from a biopsy, you can get a biopsy of muscle, build it as a ball and then we put
them all together and it turns out that once you do this, those specialized neurons in the cortex,
not every cortical neuron, but the ones that really go to the spinal cord start to leave the cortex,
find the motor neurons, then the motor neurons leave and find the muscle and then the three
preparations starts to contract. Well, that would that was a three-part assembly. All right. And
that that told us that even you know, against the odds because the probabilities for the cells to
find each other is very, very low and yet this works beautifully and you can actually stimulate
the cortex and you get beautiful muscle contractions. And we've been using this, you know,
really in the last years to identify, for instance, how polio virus and other non-polio
enteroviruses actually affect the spinal cord and cause paralysis, which is very difficult to study
otherwise. So it is a very important so like preparation, you can add this polio virus and you can
cause a paralysis of that circuit in a dish. This work is not yet published, but it tells you like
just how useful a preparation like this can be. It's beyond useful. I mean, what I'm trying to figure,
not figure out, envision is a time where we've mapped like everything, right? So you have,
you have the layout. Now, would there be a time because of what you're saying that we'll be able to
go in, identify in a child that is developing in the womb and then identify mutations and then
take the assemblots, put them into the child and have those mutations corrected before the child
is born. Is that the deal? Perhaps even an easier scenario for that. Okay. Is that have a mutation?
You know that a patient will have a serious mutation. You build an assemblot that models the
disease of that patient without using the patient brain. So like an avatar if you want, right? I mean,
that's what an assemblot is. If you think about it, right? It's an avatar for that circuit. Simplified
in a dish, you test a drug or you screen for drugs. Maybe you want to screen quickly for drugs.
Right. And then you use that in a patient. So now you can do that for every single patient. You
don't have to actually do the process in any particular patient because now you developed a drug
for the mutation itself. Now just boom, boom, boom, every single person with that mutation gets that
drug delivered and that's how you, wow, that's amazing. But you get there. We do need to get a
better understanding of how because you see where quite why do wait, why do you have to understand
why the cells do what they do? They're doing it. You already know why do you have to, are you just
a new scientist? That's right. Because he said, look at, look at Neil, look at that. We're like,
how dare you just science it. We don't accept just what is.
It actually think about like Richard Feynman. He famously said, and I'm sure you know this,
that what I cannot create, I do not understand. And you know, if you think a little bit about this,
if we cannot recreate the circuits outside, it's going to be difficult for us to understand. And if
we don't understand the biology, all the breakthroughs in medicine that came over the last decades,
think about cancer in children, right? In the 60s, 90% lethal. Today, less than 10% lethal.
Why this entire revolution, molecular biology? Because the tissue of inches was accessible. You get
the blood of these patients in leukemia or the tumor. You bring it to the lab and you deploy the
power of molecular biology. We in psychiatry and neurology are really the last ones because we
cannot access the brain. So my belief is that as we gain access to the brain through this methods
and others, noninvasively, we're going to be able to deploy the power of molecular biology and
make breakthroughs in molecular, you know, psychiatry and neurologism, we've done in, you know,
cardiology and other branches of medicine. That's sort of like how I see it, but I may be wrong.
But haven't you got an Assembloid now that's like I said, a four-stage Assembloid, but you've
worked it so as it's sensory and you can feel the understanding of pain and then how that becomes
hypersensitivity or to the point where people do not feel pain at all. Oh, okay, I thought you
meant like they're going to have that little vial of assemblies just screaming in the middle of the
night. No, why did you keep me playing? Not that one. You know, you're right that one of the things
that we're trying, actually, this just came out. I mean, we made the first Assembloid in like
2017. It took us three years to make go from two parts Assembloids to three parts Assembloids,
the one with the motor that I was explaining. And then it took us another five years to get to
four parts Assembloids just because it's technically more and more complicated. And this is the
pathway that sends is, you know, sensory information. So think about it. If you, you know, want to
sense anything, even a painful stimulus on a finger, you have nerve terminals that are coming from
neurons that sit close to the spinal cord. They have receptors that sense that then they send that
information to the spinal cord. The spinal cord shoots that information up to the thalamus in the middle
of the brain and the thalamus sent it to the cortex and then you sense that something happened.
You know, that's how it works. So what we did is essentially we tried to reconstruct that from
part. So we made neurons that have some of these receptors, including receptors for pain.
So, you know, the receptors for pain actually respond to capsacing, you know, red hot chili pepper,
that's why it's going to be a hot. So they have the specialized receptors and you add capsacing and
they just beautifully respond like electrically. But this had never been witnessed before.
No, I mean, to put the entire circuit together has never really been done before. Now,
the biology of you to witness this the first ever time. Well, the most beautiful part of it was to
be honest, once we made the parts which took us years, you know, the four parts of the circuit and
then put them together and it takes about a hundred days to make them, by the way, and then another
hundred days for the cells to connect with each other. And then at one point, we started like
looking at them and seeing like what's going on. And we've discovered something, you know, really
remarkable. The cells in the circuit become synchronized with each other. So initially, there were
all sparkling, you know, in a non coordinated way. And then at one point, the activity just seems
to be starting on one side and it goes, you know, one unit direction. So the circuit is almost,
you know, and there's no stimulus, by the way, you know, it's almost like which we know also from
brain development that the brain prepares itself before it even receives sensory inputs for what is
about to come. It's almost like practicing. So it's practicing to add, you know, the stimulus. And
then the relevance for pain is that there are this interesting, maybe you've heard about this,
neurologists discovered them, you know, in the past 20 years. There are these patients that have
mutations that make them either completely insensitive to pain. So they literally feel no pain.
And it's really caused by a mutation in a channel, in a sodium channel, or they have the opposite.
They have this channel high-percentive. So they're high-percentive to pain. Both of them are
obviously very bad. So now what we did, we used CRISPR because we were talking about CRISPR before.
And genetically modified the cells in a dish to have the mutations that are present in patients.
Then put them together all four and started watching to see what happens. And in the patients that
have that high-percentive to pain, they're very sensitive to pain, you just see the information
going really, really fast. The cells are super active and they sense it. But in the ones that have
no pain, it's not like there's no activity at all. Actually what we found is there's a lack of
coordination. The cells are essentially like lost that coordination. So that's why it's so important
to have the parts because really at the end of the day, you know, the brain is more than the sum of
its parts, obviously. And so clearly in order to understand some of these disorders, we're going to
need to have some of these parts put together to get these emergent new properties.
And just feeling pain, that's the new, that's the know the kind of movie isn't it?
Yeah, but you know, I mean, we see this in certain people that, okay, I remember we did on the
TV show and Neil has this crazy thing. He can stick his hand in water, ice water. I'm not,
and I'm not saying it right. Take a bunch of ice, add water to it and it actually becomes
colder than freezing, okay? Yes.
All right. Then you put your hand in it and it burns your hand. So we did an experiment and
I stuck my hand in and he stuck his hand in and literally my hand started burning in what a normal
person would have their hand burn. And then he was able to leave his hand in there for a god-awful
amount of time to the point where this is all you were squealing at the time. Well, yes, I was
because it burned. It was not cool. So not literally burned because it's cold, not hot.
Right. It's not literally burned. But it felt like it was burning. Okay. But for you for some
reason, and you know, I just talked it up to you. He got a lot more fat on his hands to get.
But seriously, it's a matter of sensitivity to pain. No, no, it is not. No, what is it?
I didn't say I didn't feel the pain. It is just that I could deal with it. Oh,
well, that just changes everything. Oh, no, that's okay. So explain to me the mind of a match
a respect here. That's a great point actually because you see this is not the only pathway for pain.
It turns out that we have at least two pathways in the brain. One of them allows you to tell
there is a painful stimulus. You know, I sense it. It's on my finger or my hand is in the water,
not my feet. Right. That's the one that tells you that. And then there is a second pathway
that actually leverage other brain regions, the amygdala, the singlet cortex,
that tell you that that is really bad. It gives you the unpleasant feeling, the emotional
component of pain. And you know, they're interesting. They're patients who dissociate between the two.
So their patients do, let's say, have a stroke or a tumor in the insula or in the singlet cortex.
And you'll have this patient and they'll tell you, you know, I know you're, you know,
you're hurting like my finger. And I can tell you that it is my finger, but it doesn't feel unpleasant
at all. So this pathways are dissociated in the brain. Now, in the work that we've done,
we've reconstructed the basic pathway that just processes pain stimuli, not the emotional
component. So we wouldn't say that they're feeling pain in any way, right? Just to make it clear,
because as you can imagine, there are kind of other ethical issues that are arising from like most
of the work that we do, obviously, because you know, we want our models to be closer to the
human brain because we think that many of the psychiatric disorders are uniquely human. And yet,
the more the closer they are to the human brain, the more uncomfortable we feel, right? So I think
it's so like mitigating this risk moving forward that I think is very important. How do you now
having had this experience with the sensory aspect of it, reverse engineer again, the way to
get a drug to alleviate the hypersensitivity to pain? Sure. I mean, there are many ways that you
can do this. So like, no, think about it. Scott Scott. Well, not everybody, everybody's got to
think with opioids, but there must be a mechanism there where opioids use that you can sort of tag
on to, but not get that addictive part. Exactly. And think about it, like it's sad that the best,
the best treatment that we have for like pain comes out of like poppy season,
and what discovered thousands of years ago by chance, right? I mean, essentially piggybacks on
this circuit does not come from a deep understanding of the circuit itself. Don't you make opium from
poppy seeds? Yes. Okay. Just want to clarify that. Yeah. So I think the idea now is that we have
the circuit in a dish. You can add opioids by the way and see how they modulate this and see,
okay, this is what opioids do to the circuit. But let's now try to do the same thing in a different
way, right? One that is sort of like, you know, driven by the biology behind it. And I think
that's the beauty of it. That is a beauty. And by the way, a professor, if you ever get to that
place, please email me right before you make that public because I would like to be the first investor
in the pain free opiate that is non addictive because that is, I mean, that's the end of the game
right there. And just to be clear, Chuck, what? Because when my hand was I just want to like,
get back to my hand in the bucket. Yeah. Okay. Long ago, right when I began wrestling in high school.
And I was going to bring this up. I think it's because you were an athlete and athletes have to
deal with pain all the time. Exactly. And I judge by looking at the situation, is this pain,
something that will cause irreparable damage or is it just simply pain? Okay. And I'm looking at
my hand is in a bucket of ice. Yeah, it hurts. But I love who cares. I'm not going to get
frostbite from it. Okay. So you and Gary have that I'm sure because Gary's had a ton of surgery.
We have not played in pain. He sat in ice after games. Right. See, and I have not played
in none of that. I've done none of that. And this is you play. That's why you went out in the time
of me because this is how pain works for me. Okay. The way pain works for me is I experience it
and then my brain, my body and everything in my soul goes, Jesus, no, please Lord, no. So,
so when when you're saying you're you're building these avatars and the detective work that comes,
are you finding more clues and more answers or are you just finding clues and then we've got to sit
there, scratch your heads and hopefully come up with an answer. Or is this really empowering
the sort of psychiatric research that you're interested in? You know, the way I look at it is,
you know, psychiatric disorders have been a mystery like no doubt. I mean, how does complex
behavior or hallucination arises from the brain in mesmerizing us for such a long time? And it's
almost like if you were to think about it, it's almost as like seeing, you know, Egyptians riding
for the first time, right? You look at them, you know, where do you even start? I mean,
they're beautiful drawings, you know, you could classify them based on like the animals,
but then you can make sense of what the meaning is. And you see, that's why, you know, if you think
about it, like historically, the discovery of the Rosetta stone, right? Like this tiny piece
tablet that for the first time had ear glips on one side and Greek riding on the other one,
right? And then, you know, this French scientist, we came with Napoleon, finds this,
starts looking at it. And that becomes essentially the, you know, enabling tool.
Suddenly, we could actually see what word does what? And you know, cool thing about the Rosetta
stone. It's like a shopping list or something. It's like, it's not really any deep, just like
bread eggs. I don't know exactly a shopping list, but it's something completely very, very
yet, but yeah, really trivial. Absolutely. And yet, like, it was the only riding that we know
that have both on both sides. So I think the question is, we need to somehow translate that one
point. So like this mental processes that are so complex into what we can deal with, which is
really molecular biology. That's what we can control. Well, like, molecular biology, we can control.
So I think, you know, to a large extent, I've seen this like the, the mission, you know,
for my lab. And in general, like I think for the community more broadly, is really to try
to translate some of this complex phenomena of the brain in very simple processes,
calcium in a neuron, you know, tuneros connecting with each other. And then, hopefully by doing that,
and finding ways of reversing it, those will also reverse at least improve. We don't know that,
you know, we, we, you know, that has not yet been done. And, you know, we'll have to see what the
clinical trial will actually be successful. I mean, we're preparing for clinical trial for
Timothy syndrome right now. We're still like in the last stages of preparation. We found most of the
patients in the world were building a special unit here, Stanford, where we're going to be
hopefully bringing them in the next year or so and doing the clinical trial. So we'll see. And then,
you know, this is the first disease. I mean, and I look at Timothy syndrome, so like really being
the first first, but we have half a dozen of other conditions that we've been studying from various
angles. Really, I mean, I see this, this is going to be the golden age for human neuroscience.
And I'm delighted to learn that you're putting in this much effort for a disease that is so rare.
Yeah. I mean, think about that. So the rarity, at least the people have the benefit of your
attention given to it. Yeah. Rather than someone just making the cost benefit analysis. And say,
we're not doing anything. We're not going there. We're not going down that. Right. Yeah. Right.
So I'll be saying here that your
assembly research and work is going to be the key to understanding what has been hidden
brain biology. How soon do you think maybe you really will be able to not just tick off the
Timothy syndrome, but take on other horrific diseases? Oh, we're already working on others.
I mean, you know, at least half a dozen we've been studying. Like some are associated with
epilepsy, somewhat intellectual disability. We have a few forms of schizophrenia. So we didn't
deploying this like systematically. And another thing that we've done to be honest, and this is sort
like being in the spirit of what we do at Stanford is, you know, I lead us to a center here.
And in the beginning, it was, you know, there was when we published some of the first methods,
everybody was like, Oh, you know, can we come to the lab and learn how to do it? Like we want to do
it too. And we brought people here initially, but at one point, you know, we couldn't train
enough people. So we actually started doing literally courses where we bring students from all
over the world from various labs. And for about a week, almost like in a cooking show, if you
want to think about it, right? Because you know, the experiments are done before. We just show them,
this are the critical steps that you need to do. And so we've been helping more than 300 labs
around the world to, you know, implement this method. And if the breakthrough is not going to come
from my lab, therapeutically speaking, that's fine. Because it will probably come from somebody else,
somewhere like, you know, in a corner of Europe or who knows of South America doing experiments on
a rare form of disease and finding a therapeutic, that would be fine. I think because there's so much to
do for, you know, one in four individuals is suffers from a psychiatric disease today. All right.
It's a huge burden. Are we going to come across a situation where you are going to have you be
faced with building an assembler, it or creating an assembler that will just be too complex?
Is there a limit to what you can assemble? There are absolutely limits to what we can assemble.
And, you know, while like many of the features of this assembler is really fascinating and
surprising, you know, they still have a lot of limitations. You know, I mean, they're not
vasterized. They don't receive blood supply. We may be able to stimulate them with like
capsules and something else, but they're not receiving the rich sensory information that is important.
You know, think about the, you know, if you have a kitten where you, you know, you cover one eye,
you cover that eye for a week, that cat will never see with that eye. You do it in an adult cat
for a week, no problem whatsoever. So early in development, if some of the circuits do not
receive the right input, they won't develop properly. So, you know, again, while our models are
relatively complex already, they lack a lot of the complexity. And, you know, is as George
box famously said, that all models are wrong or some are useful, you know, and the models that we make
are not, our goal is not to make a perfect model of the brain. It's like to make a good enough
model of a part of a brain over a circuit that will give us the brain through therapeutically.
I wouldn't be so harsh with the term model there. I would say all models are almost by construct
incomplete, right? But that wouldn't make them wrong necessarily. They're just, they're not the
whole story. That's why they're a model. Otherwise would be the exact thing. You would need it.
You would need a model if you could replicate the exact thing. It would be the thing. Right.
It's all right. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. I just love that assembloids sounds like a cartoon network show.
Like assembloids weekdays at three right after Transformers. You know, it's actually
that's how there is a game. There is a video game for it, which I didn't know when I put out the
term, but there is a very popular video game that is literally called assemblids. Cool.
Where do we hit the ethical wall and hit the regulatory and all the other things? And
do you say regulatory? I did. This America Jack is regulatory. I'm not even regulatory.
I'm not even regulatory. I didn't come here for a lecture on geography. I know it's America.
It's a murky Jack. Anyway, we were saying, you know, we think about this like all the time.
Honestly, in the beginning, obviously, they're like not that many ethical issues, but as we've
progressed, it becomes clear that we have to think carefully. So they're like, you know, the way
I think I was is like in multiple levels. Like on one hand, they're like issues about the cells.
These are human cells that we're using. Yeah. You know, who owns the cells? You have to give
consent for this experiment to be done. And we do that all the time. And so we always have to put
that into the context of like, what are we doing with the cells? What the cells were consented for?
That's very much like who is the woman who lacks? What's her name?
Wax. Lax. Yes. Whose cancer cells were? Who's used for decades and saved and created many
breakthroughs in cancer. And the family got nothing. And she never gave permission. So it's good
to know you're doing that. And that's why it's critical every time with every time we've got
this. Henry had a wax. Henry had a wax. Yes. You know, the patients or, you know, who,
you know, the parents, in the case of their minors will actually be clearly informed about what
will happen with the cells, how the cells will be shared with others, for instance, under what
conditions and so on and so forth. So on one hand, there are like this issues about the cells.
Then sometimes as you know, we're using animals. So sometimes we transplant this into the animal.
So we also have to think about the well for urban animal. I mean, you transplant more is the
animal suffering in any way. And then the third problem, which is perhaps the more con like
philosophical in a way is like, are there any new emergent properties? Like are there,
you know, features, complex features that are rising from this that would make one thing that we
need to regulate this field? Currently, I think the models that we have in feature are not sufficiently
complex to justify, you know, the presence of any complex features. Like that's why we don't
use the term generally, you know, the term intelligence for this because intelligence is really a
property of an organism. It involves like gold directed behavior, involves learning. None of our
cultures do that. And using, you know, anthropomorphizing, it's not generally a very useful thing to do
in this case. But as the models become more complex, we have to start having this conversations.
And that's why, you know, last year we had an Estilumar meeting, which is like this historic
place here in California, you may have heard where many of this ethical discussions have started
in biology in the 70s when cloning, gene cloning was so like discovered that everybody was like,
what is going to happen? We're now modifying these genes and we're going to create new organisms.
So scientists got together there with philosophers, you know, with journalists. So that's what we're
also doing now. We're getting together a larger group and thinking what are some of the implications?
You know, sociologically, religiously, philosophically, while at the same time, thinking that
psychiatric disorders are a huge burden. And if you have a technology that has the potential
to change that, to provide cures, is it, you know, unethical not to use it? Right? I mean,
there's even that argument, you know, where, you know, how far do we go in that? So that those
are like ongoing discussions. I mean, it's been really interesting. I spend more and more
over my time as part of this conversation. Let me take just one other place before we land the plane
here. You came into this as an expert in the autism spectrum patient. Yes. And a new term that's
been bandied about the last certainly 10 years is the concept of neurodiversity. When you look at it
that way, who was anyone to say that someone needs repair if they're simply manifesting on a
spectrum of neurodiversity? Sure. Your counterparts not long ago would have labeled homosexuality
as a mental disorder in need of repair. And only recently, been historical times recently,
was that removed from the list of human maladies and disorders. So there's an ethical,
another ethical frontier about what it is you judge needs repair versus is just another kind of
person. And that's absolutely one of the discussions that we've been having, one of the ethical
discussions that we've been having. And you know, all psychiatric disorders are on a spectrum with
the population. And some of them are more severe and some of them are less severe. And that's also the
case for autism. You know, autism is certainly a spectrum. But what we're focusing on is actually
what we now call profound autism. This is the autism that is really debilitating. So patients with
Timothy syndrome or like some of the other patients that were like with other disorders can have
60 seizures a day. Oh, really? That's just they are unable to make any eye contact. They need a
caregiver for the rest of their life. You know, the biggest fear that a parent has when they have,
you know, a child is like, what if I die? So I am seeing it through the eyes of some of this
parents that are dealing with like really the devastating forms of autism, what we call profound
autism. And then of course, there is like what you mentioned, which are neurotypical or,
you know, aspects of how we interact with each other that do not require any, nobody wants
to cure or to provide treatment for anybody. But this patient are severely affected. Most
patients with psychiatric disorders are severely affected. So I once asked Oliver Sacks,
who is a friend of our show. We have some archival content with him. Oh, that's amazing. Yeah,
yeah. I asked him after a public talk that he gave, if you could go back in time and carry with
you a pill that would cure your own elements, uh, get sort of certain neuro issues. Uh, he has,
correct me on the word here, prognoplagnesia. Yes, he did. Yeah, he couldn't really identify
the face blindness. Okay. Oh, wow. And and some other elements to it. Sometimes wish I had that.
Oh, okay. So, so I asked him, if you could take a pill that would just cure that back when you were
17, would you looking back at that time? And he said, no, because it was that those differences in
the way his mind worked, they got him interested in neuroscience. That was his destiny. But,
but you see, that's exactly, you know, the point where we started, like the beauty of like building
a nervous system is that while there is a basic plan that makes our brains the same, we pretty
might, you know, can do the same things. It also creates a lot of diversity, even monozigotic twins,
right? I have the same genetic, uh, you know, material, they share the same womb. Yeah. And then
they can have different sexual orientations, you know, they like, they have different hobbies.
They have different fingerprints, if I remember correctly, don't they? They do. They do. Yes.
Wow. Because again, there is a lot of stochastic forces in development. And those are the,
those are the ones that make us different. And that's how evolution actually works too. You know,
by selecting these differences that, yeah, I mean, to large extent probably that's what made us
as a species so successful. Yeah. The fact that there's always an individual who has a vision,
who wants to go and, you know, discover a new continent. Yeah. So I think that's the power of our
species. And I think I know very few, honestly, psychiatrist or neurologist who would want to cure
that or change that. Right. Right. I think what we're dealing really on the field is really
this devastated conditions that make essentially most of this children unable to really function as
as adults or as children. So it's a very human human-centric view. So if you were the,
the COVID virus, you would say, let's invent humans who then have airplanes so that we can cross
continents and affect other people. Absolutely. They are the true owners of this planet.
Let's be on the virus. They're true owners of this planet.
Micrubs. We're just a new bus. Yeah. That's all. We're just an Uber ride. Well,
Sergio, it's been a delight to have you on StarTalk sharing your expertise with us and taking time
out of what we know is your busy research schedule. Give us a little glimpse into what you're doing
in your lab. Just congratulations to you and all the people who work in your lab who are surely
working there right now while you're talking to us. Right here. I mean, yeah.
And really, they're the ones doing well in the work. I mean, you know, this work, I mean,
hopefully it came through from the discussions, but this experiments are long. I mean, they last
hundreds of days because human element it takes a long time. So it requires a lot of dedication.
And I, but I think the promise of what this could yield ultimately, you know, understanding
the human brain is, you know, is addictive. So, you know, we really want to figure this out.
Well, thank you again. I'd like to reflect on this with a brief cosmic perspective. If I may,
please. This moving neuroscience frontier has got me thinking.
We look at the progress of civilization. It always comes about when we have the proper match
between the tool and a goal. And when they come together, we build thing that didn't exist before.
But we disassemble things that had never been taken apart before. But in all cases, it has to do
with the precision of the tools you bring to the task. And to learn what's going on on the frontier
of neuroscience, it feels to me that it's finally catching up with the methods and tools that
have shaped engineering throughout the history of civilization. Engineers built
dams and building and aqueducts and everything that we value and care about in our modern life.
But the time has come to care about what's going on inside our brain within our mind. And I'm
delighted to learn that that is a frontier that finally has tools befitting the task.
Welcome to the club. Neuroscience. And that is a cosmic perspective. Keep looking up.